<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Addiction on BonnyCode</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/addiction/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Addiction on BonnyCode</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 12:27:25 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/addiction/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Short-term metrics, long-term harm</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/short-term-metrics-long-term-harm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 12:27:25 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/short-term-metrics-long-term-harm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the early 90s, I found a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multi-user_dungeon&#34;&gt;MUD&lt;/a&gt; (a so-called Multi-User Dungeon game) called Apocalypse by telnetting into an IP address from a book (with a silly name like &amp;ldquo;The Whole Internet catalog for dummies&amp;rdquo;) I&amp;rsquo;d bought at a computer fair. It bore resemblance to Advanced Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons (2nd edition) that I played sitting around a table with friends; just a pure text version you could play with randos on the internet instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You started at level 1 killing rats for experience points. After you gained enough experience points, you leveled up, and your character became more powerful. Then you killed slimes, and goblins, and later trolls and dragons as your power grew. Unlike AD&amp;amp;D, which required walking to a friend&amp;rsquo;s house and coordinating schedules, MUDs were always there. Always waiting. Just one more level..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I soon became a dealer. I gave my school friends access to my internet provider so they could play too. We competed to see who could level fastest. We feigned illness to skip school and grind all day. My grades suffered. School was boring anyway though. Completing one more dungeon, getting better gear, just one more level was so much more satisfying than learning about arctangents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-big-tech-launches-features-through-ab-testing&#34;&gt;How big tech launches features through A/B testing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The de facto way tech companies test and launch new product functionality is via an A/B test. In its simplest form, an A/B test is an experiment where you randomly allocate half of a population to control (how things work today) and half to a treatment (the new thing you want to test). This allows you to know with statistical significance even very small changes in how people use your product. As in, when we tweak our recommendation algorithm in this way we are &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confidence_interval&#34;&gt;95% confident&lt;/a&gt; it will make people on average spend 11 to 16 more seconds on our application. What a win! Ship it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty of A/B tests is they move product debates from wild speculation to evidence-based answers. Rather than bet your company&amp;rsquo;s future on one big change, you can instead make thousands of little bets and keep just the ones that move you ever forward towards your company&amp;rsquo;s KPIs. It no longer matters WHY it works, just that you can prove it does work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure what effect adding likes to stories will have?  No reason to debate. Just try it out. Oh, looks like people post more stories when given the positive signal of likes. Great! Ship it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;skepticism-of-experimentation&#34;&gt;Skepticism of experimentation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a company like Amazon, Deming&amp;rsquo;s quote &amp;ldquo;in God we trust, all others bring data&amp;rdquo; was accepted as a foundational principle. In 2017, I was brought in to lead Snap’s (maker of Snapchat) data organization. It was a culture shock when I found people talking about data-informed decision making rather than data-driven decision making. To my Amazon-trained mind it sounded no better than vibe driven decision making; a way for product managers to just launch whatever they felt like, damn the data. And don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, it was that sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it wasn&amp;rsquo;t just that. Likes on friend stories? Preemptively vetoed by Evan, Snap’s CEO. Not because it wouldn’t pass an A/B test (it would almost certainly be bright green and green normally means “LET’S GOO”), but because Evan thought it was harmful to users. There was a constant murmur from the product team about what tests Evan would allow and not allow, and it was almost entirely driven by Evan’s sense of what was detrimental to people who used the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had deleted my Facebook account in 2010 and was shockingly ignorant of the ills of social media. I knew it wasn’t something I enjoyed, I recognized it wasn’t great for my own mental health, but live and let live, right? To those who grew up on social media though and could pierce the veil, it was a world where social media companies (which really just meant Facebook and friends) blindly used experimentation to drive up time spent. And that their relentless drive for time spent had real and negative consequences for their users; from building up echo chambers of fake news to creating new generations of mental health decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;beyond-good-and-evil&#34;&gt;Beyond good and evil&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evan isn’t the hero of this story because there are no heroes. The quicker we move away from heroes and villains, the sooner we can embrace making better ethical decisions in our daily life. In this case though, and largely with the benefit of hindsight, I believe Evan was mostly right for mostly the right reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Snap, it was not a controversial take to say that Facebook was evil and we were “better” than them. Not better because we built a more profitable business (ha!), but because we were inarguably cooler and not so evil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moral judgements are tricky things though. Everyone is the hero of their own story. How easy it is for those of us in tech to be seduced by RSUs and stock prices. It can be life-changing money. You give to good causes. You are just making your users love the application more and getting paid to do it. Is that wrong? At least you don’t work for a defense contractor, designing missiles that kill innocent people in lands faraway. Right?
The funny thing when you have an evil company like Facebook to compare yourself to, is it becomes so easy to excuse your own transgressions. If I had a nickel for every time someone at Snap did something they knew was wrong but said “I’m one of the good guys, you should see what (Facebook|Engineering|Product Management) do!” The evil that does exist, if it does, in our everyday life is perpetuated by people who consider themselves good but still find a way to ignore the negative consequences they have on others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-root-causes-matter&#34;&gt;Why root causes matter&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing Amazon did really well was a process called Correction of Error (COE). When a problem occurs (such as oops, a new hire just took down AWS), you ask &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_whys&#34;&gt;5 Whys&lt;/a&gt;, and get down to the root cause. You then create mechanisms to prevent not only that error, but that entire class of errors from occurring again. Amazon didn&amp;rsquo;t invent root cause analysis, but they made it part of their culture of success more so than anywhere else I&amp;rsquo;ve ever worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media = doom scrolling, social media = poor mental health, social media = bad, I&amp;rsquo;m not some revolutionary making this connection. I&amp;rsquo;m honestly 15 years too late if that was the point here. The question is WHY. How were they able to hone such an addiction machine? It didn&amp;rsquo;t have to be their intent. It is a natural consequence of doing what most tech companies now consider to be the gold standard and investors celebrate. Most good investor outcomes lead from more time spent. It means higher retention, it means more ad surface (if that&amp;rsquo;s your jam), it means better conversion. What is the easiest way to increase time spent? To make people addicted. It requires no more intent than natural selection does, just thousands upon thousands of little experiments surviving by tapping into our addiction centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What root causes allow us to do is move past just looking at the incidentals. I dislike the phrase “if you are not paying for the product, you are the product”, not because it isn’t true, but because it is a deflection. Social media’s negative externalities aren’t due to it being an ad-driven model. If people paid subscriptions for Facebook, it wouldn’t change the damage it did. It is a great quote if you are Steve Jobs and playing hide the rabbit (who conveniently didn’t have an ad-driven business model). Root causes allow you to move past all of that and ask, what actually led to the problem at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;addiction&#34;&gt;Addiction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christmas morning, late 90s, I had been playing a MUD since 5am. It was now late morning and I was still playing. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t hanging out with my family, they knew not to bother me. I was just grinding. One more level.
I still played games after that, but something broke in me that day. What was I doing with my life? All for bits on a computer server somewhere to increment one more time. It seemed so meaningful. When Everquest and then World of Warcraft came out and the world of visual MUDs (now rebranded as MMORPGs) arrived, I played them but could never get into them. Whatever snapped in me that Christmas morning meant I could never get hooked again like I once was. But I saw in others the same spiral of addiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experimentation didn&amp;rsquo;t invent tech addiction. But it gave tech companies the tool to refine it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-bliss-point&#34;&gt;The bliss point&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a new battle. Technology has given us new ways to hack human desire since the industrial revolution, but we&amp;rsquo;ve seen this movie before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Food scientists discovered something they call the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bliss_point_(food)&#34;&gt;bliss point&lt;/a&gt; – the precise combination of sugar, fat, and salt that makes you unable to stop eating. Howard Moskowitz pioneered this in the 70s, using experimentation and mathematical models to find the exact formula that would hijack your taste buds. Just one more soda. Just one more chip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On paper, it looks like capitalism working perfectly. Companies make more delicious products. Consumers freely choose to buy them. Everyone wins. Except we&amp;rsquo;re now decades into dealing with an obesity epidemic that&amp;rsquo;s killing us. Turns out that optimizing for what people want in the moment is different from optimizing for what keeps them healthy. The processed food industry A/B tested their way to our addiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;and-history-repeats-itself&#34;&gt;And history repeats itself&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding root causes means you can be more targeted in how you mitigate risk for the future. We talk a lot about alignment with LLMs, but we&amp;rsquo;ve been faced with a larger alignment problem between technology and free market capitalism for a century now. How do we align short-term consumer signals to long-term positive values for those same consumers? This is not an easy problem. Who decides what the long-term positive values are? How long does long-term need to be? Companies struggle to even understand long-term effects of features as it is. That is why short-term metrics are so often prioritized. Nobody says it is an easy problem; do we only take on easy problems though?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It shouldn&amp;rsquo;t catch us by surprise when the makers of LLMs, pulling out the same tech playbook, start optimizing models based on these same principles. Why is model A better than model B? Because an A/B test says it leads to more frequent and longer chat sessions. Is that because the model is providing more value to human lives or is it because the model tells people what they want to hear? We&amp;rsquo;re already seeing this play out. We should question if LLM sycophantic responses (&amp;lsquo;What a thoughtful question, now you&amp;rsquo;re thinking like an expert!&amp;rsquo;) are bugs or merely models that tested better on short-term engagement. What happens when models that challenge users, correct misconceptions, or refuse to engage in harmful activity score lower on engagement metrics in the A/B test? Does it matter when our models agree with conspiracy theorists rather than educating them? Who cares, A/B test is green, ship it! 🚢&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are the consequences of raising a new generation on this? Imagine a teenager whose AI tutor never corrects their mistakes because confrontation reduces session time. Or a lonely user whose chatbot companion validates harmful thought patterns because pushing back might end the conversation. We&amp;rsquo;re optimizing for engagement, not human flourishing. Who cares, A/B test is green, ship it! 🚢🚢🚢&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We already can predict how this story ends because it has happened before. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen it with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1550830723002847&#34;&gt;processed food&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/facebook-instagram-dangerous-content-60-minutes-2022-12-11/&#34;&gt;social media&lt;/a&gt;, with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/9777818/&#34;&gt;tobacco industry&lt;/a&gt;, with every technology that learned to hack human desire. Will we pretend we didn&amp;rsquo;t know the consequences once more?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;it-is-easier-to-identify-problems-than-solve-them&#34;&gt;It is easier to identify problems than solve them&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As professionals building these apps, we are in a difficult situation. Evan could veto addictive features because he was CEO. A junior (or even senior) data scientist flagging that same thing? At the very least, it can put a ceiling on your career at that company. Data scientists and software engineers simply don’t have the institutional support. Even for me as someone who was a leader, who had access to boards, the ear of the c-suite, bringing up ethical issues frankly makes people uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why are you airing our dirty laundry?&amp;rdquo; As if acknowledging an issue was worse than causing it. &amp;ldquo;This is just how it is done.&amp;rdquo; Meaning, if others in industry do it then it is fair game. &amp;ldquo;Senior leaders focus on outcomes, not academic philosophy.&amp;rdquo; Outcomes, of course, meaning quarterly goals, not whether we&amp;rsquo;re making human lives better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing like the professional independence a structural engineer or financial auditor has baked into their roles. For now, we are left with asking professionals to square their ethics with their need to make a living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When that Christmas morning shattered my MUD addiction, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t through willpower or intervention. It was through sudden, painful clarity about what I was actually doing. The mechanics became visible. Kill mob, get XP, level up, repeat. Once I saw through the meaninglessness of it, I couldn’t unsee it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is our first defense: understanding. When you understand how products are engineered to  keep you scrolling 16 more seconds (one A/B test at a time), when you recognize that &amp;ldquo;likes&amp;rdquo; are engineered to trigger your social validation circuits, when you see the bliss point being calibrated in real time, the spell weakens. Not completely, but, at least for me, it has been enough to matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The processed food industry isn&amp;rsquo;t reforming because food scientists revolted. Rather, public health awareness, nutritional education, and media exposure increased consumer demand for healthier options, driving industry change.  The same transparency that let me see through MUDs&amp;rsquo; mechanics can work here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are building these addiction machines. We can build something else. Not through individual heroics or professional martyrdom, but through collective awareness and incremental resistance. The question isn&amp;rsquo;t whether we can create non-addictive technology. We can. The question is whether enough of us will choose to, now that we know the cost of what we&amp;rsquo;ve been building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My MUD addiction was innocent compared to what we&amp;rsquo;re building now. Those games were made by college students who loved playing them, not optimized by thousands of experiments. Today&amp;rsquo;s products are different. They&amp;rsquo;re industrial strength. That&amp;rsquo;s exactly why understanding their mechanics matters more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
