<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Career &amp; Professional on BonnyCode</title>
    <link>https://www.bonnycode.com/categories/career--professional/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Career &amp; Professional on BonnyCode</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.bonnycode.com/categories/career--professional/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Where feedback goes to die</title>
      <link>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/where-feedback-goes-to-die/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/where-feedback-goes-to-die/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a cabinet above my espresso maker where unused gifts go to sit. For each gift I said thank you, and it felt disrespectful to later throw them away, so they sit there for years. Acknowledged yet untouched; quietly accumulating[^1].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cabinet is what we used to jokingly call write-only storage. A physical manifestation of gratitude and obligation, but really just a way of postponing honesty. There are ideas, observations, and judgments we receive in much the same way: politely accepted, carefully stored, and just as carefully kept from interfering with how we live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feedback often ends up there. Thank the person offering it, assume good intent,  reassure ourselves that we&amp;rsquo;ve heard it. And then place it somewhere out of sight, where it can&amp;rsquo;t trouble the assumptions we were already acting on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feedback matters because it is one of the few ways we ever learn that we are wrong. Most of us can go on for years acting on assumptions that no longer fit the world. Especially when those assumptions make us feel competent, justified, or familiar with ourselves. Without something that pushes back, error doesn&amp;rsquo;t correct itself. It simply settles in and becomes the often invisible background of our decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;knowing-when-were-wrong&#34;&gt;Knowing when we&amp;rsquo;re wrong&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some ideas are structured so that nothing can ever count against them. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m just bad at math&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;people are always out to get me.&amp;rdquo; Self-fulfilling prophecies that stop functioning as explanations and instead are just comforting stories we tell ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve found that one way to guard against this is to be clear, before acting, about what I expect to happen if I&amp;rsquo;m right. Without clearly set in advance, it is too easy to reinterpret any outcome as a success after the fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I design a course, for example, I expect students to struggle at certain points and also have an idea of when that should resolve for most students. I often introduce implementation ambiguity early on because I believe it serves a pedagogical purpose. If students express some discomfort in how they should solve a problem in the first week, that feedback doesn&amp;rsquo;t challenge my course design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that only works if there’s a point where continued struggle would force me to rethink the design. I have to be specific about what confusion I expect, and what outcomes should justify it by the end. Otherwise, I’m just building up an excuse for unclear instruction as “intentional ambiguity,” and the line between pedagogy and sloppiness disappears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same pattern shows up in how we talk about ourselves. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m just someone who speaks my mind, it&amp;rsquo;s not my fault if people can&amp;rsquo;t handle it&amp;rdquo; resembles a description, but it serves as a shield. The question worth asking isn&amp;rsquo;t whether it feels true, but whether there&amp;rsquo;s any feedback that would make us reconsider it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;feedback-isnt-a-score&#34;&gt;Feedback isn&amp;rsquo;t a score&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve seen people fail to accept compliments as often as they fail to accept criticism. We assume people are &amp;ldquo;just being nice.&amp;rdquo; Sometimes that&amp;rsquo;s fine — if people tell you you&amp;rsquo;re beautiful all day it&amp;rsquo;s probably good not to let it go to your head. On the other hand, if your students tell you that you look like Minecraft Steve, well, welcome to my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.bonnycode.com/minecraft-steve.png&#34; alt=&#34;I don&amp;rsquo;t see the resemblance to Minecraft Steve.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when people consistently praise our skills and we wave it off, we end up underestimating what we&amp;rsquo;re ready for. We don&amp;rsquo;t take on challenges we could handle because we discount positive signal as easily as negative. Feedback isn&amp;rsquo;t only useful for correction. It&amp;rsquo;s often the push we need to take on something bigger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is how we frame it. If feedback is primarily evaluation (good or bad, constructive or unhelpful) then our job is to judge whether it&amp;rsquo;s accurate. Judging is a short step from dismissing. Not &amp;ldquo;is it true?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;is it fair?&amp;rdquo; but &amp;ldquo;what does it mean that someone walked away holding this belief?&amp;rdquo; Does that change anything?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a director at Amazon, long, long ago, someone on my team once told me I was scary. After they got to know me, they realized I wasn&amp;rsquo;t as scary&amp;hellip; but they were still a little scared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first reaction was that this seemed ridiculous. I&amp;rsquo;m not scary; I&amp;rsquo;m kind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked what made them feel that way. They said in meetings, when people would say things, I would tear apart their arguments, ask how they knew something to be true. They worried that if they spoke, they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to back up what they said. I did it in a &amp;ldquo;nice&amp;rdquo; way (calm, smiling), but that almost made it worse. Like I was an analytical machine ready to point out their every flaw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounded like good leadership. I was an Amazonian; I was &lt;em&gt;insisting on high standards&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;diving deep&lt;/em&gt;, teaching my team to &lt;em&gt;be right, a lot&lt;/em&gt;. Those instincts got me to where I was. But by then I was a director with a large team, and the way you act carries more weight when you have power over people&amp;rsquo;s careers. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t encouraging rigor. I was shutting down conversation. At least when I was in the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-is-worth-listening-to&#34;&gt;Who is worth listening to?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I give feedback to students or employees, they usually want more. More than I often feel I can give. They&amp;rsquo;re gracious and frequently grateful. They ask follow-up questions. The dynamic is easy. I have credibility; I&amp;rsquo;m expected to evaluate; and what I say might affect their grade or their career. Everything lines up. Most people can tell themselves they are open to feedback. Because in some situations, when delivered by some people, they are eager to listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reverse the direction and see how quickly this falls apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upward feedback, and I&amp;rsquo;m using that term broadly, is easy to dismiss. &amp;ldquo;Who are you to tell me how to do my job?&amp;rdquo; Subordinate to manager, patient to doctor, student to teacher, user to product manager. And, often, the skepticism is warranted; people without expertise tend to give bad advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &amp;ldquo;Arthur Writes a Story,&amp;rdquo; Arthur asks for feedback on a simple story about a boy finding his puppy. Each person suggests adding their favorite element from their own stories. They are not so much engaging with Arthur&amp;rsquo;s story as they are invested in their own. By the end, Arthur&amp;rsquo;s story has metamorphasized into a science fiction rock opera comedy about space-elephants. &amp;ldquo;Listen to feedback&amp;rdquo; cannot mean &amp;ldquo;do whatever people tell you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.bonnycode.com/arthur-elephant.png&#34; alt=&#34;Arthur&amp;rsquo;s story goes off the rails.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a mistake to treat this insight as a license to dismiss categories of feedback entirely. The signal is rarely the literal suggestion. Arthur&amp;rsquo;s friends gave bad advice, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean they couldn&amp;rsquo;t still provide useful feedback. The real skill is taking the time to understand why someone reacted the way they did, not just what they proposed as a solution. And then innovate based on what that reaction tells you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we reject feedback because it&amp;rsquo;s framed poorly or comes from someone without expertise, we lose the ability to understand how the people affected by our work are actually receiving it. A patient can&amp;rsquo;t tell a doctor how to practice medicine. But a patient knows when they feel unheard, confused, or scared. That&amp;rsquo;s a valuable perspective only they can give. Ignoring it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make you more expert. It just makes you blind to how it feels to be on the receiving end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;genuine-feedback-is-earned&#34;&gt;Genuine feedback is earned&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who don&amp;rsquo;t like us sometimes say things to hurt us. But, especially in professional contexts, they are often stating something true. The truth is often a better weapon than pure falsehood. I saw this pattern repeatedly as a manager and now as a teacher. Two people would not get along. They&amp;rsquo;d both point out the other person&amp;rsquo;s flaws. The criticism was often wrapped in assumed bad intentions, but underneath it calls out something observably true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Jack has no respect for other people. He is always late to meetings and when he does arrive derails the conversation to talk about things that don&amp;rsquo;t matter.&amp;rdquo; Is this feedback framed well? No. Does it give us some signal we can learn from, especially when combined with other details and perspectives? Absolutely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every blunt response like above, you&amp;rsquo;d get its more oblique cousin. &amp;ldquo;I love Jack, he is so helpful. It can be disruptive sometimes though how he arrives late to our morning meeting. I know he takes the bus here, and it isn&amp;rsquo;t really his fault, but maybe we can move the meeting?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you deliver the feedback, &amp;ldquo;it is important that you arrive on time for our morning meeting.&amp;rdquo; The response is too often either &amp;ldquo;I can&amp;rsquo;t help it&amp;rdquo; or, far worse, &amp;ldquo;who said that?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The urge is understandable. Negative anonymous feedback makes me want to play detective about who said it. If I can discredit the source’s motives or expertise, I don’t have to engage with the substance. But that habit leads to a dark, unproductive relationship with feedback. It’s healthier to start by treating it in good faith unless you have evidence otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dangerous part of this reaction is that even if you are right, you are signaling how you handle feedback. If you react with anger, or defensively, or sullenly, it causes those who value their relationship with you to hesitate next time. They learn to circle around. The unvarnished truth becomes something only your detractors will offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you respond differently, with genuine curiosity and visible change, then giving you feedback becomes a relationship-strengthening act. People who care about you start to speak up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honest feedback from someone who cares about you is often not a gift; it is something you&amp;rsquo;ve earned through your reactions to feedback in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching real lessons with fake worlds</title>
      <link>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/teaching-real-lessons-fake-worlds/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/teaching-real-lessons-fake-worlds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I build little worlds full of adventurers, potions, and dragons. Students run potion shops where they manage magical supply chains for demanding fighters and wizards. They run media companies providing entertainment to dragons, frog-folk, and discerning gnomes. And in the process, they become curious about how the worlds themselves work and come alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked in tech for a long time, most of it leading technical teams. I kept noticing the same thing: new grads who struggled with problems that looked nothing like their coursework. They knew how to do the work, but only if it was carefully packaged for them. In the wild, solving a technical problem is a cycle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Formulate:&lt;/strong&gt; Translate an unbounded, ambiguous situation into a technical problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solve:&lt;/strong&gt; Execute the technical solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interpret:&lt;/strong&gt; Evaluate whether your solution actually solved the problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even when toy problems attempt steps 1 and 3, it&amp;rsquo;s often thin pseudocontext. There isn&amp;rsquo;t enough noise, and it&amp;rsquo;s painfully obvious what technical thing needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Large language models have made this gap impossible to ignore. Step 2—doing the technical work—is now too often solvable with a prompt→copy→paste. It&amp;rsquo;s the same shift calculators brought to arithmetic: the execution is automated, but the framing of the problem is not. Simulations let me push students into Steps 1 and 3, where intellectual work continues to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve incorporated simulations into my upper-division computer science courses to teach the metacognitive and epistemic skills necessary to solve difficult problems as they actually exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-simulation&#34;&gt;Why Simulation?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always loved simulation-style games. Ever since playing the gold-cartridge &lt;em&gt;Legend of Zelda&lt;/em&gt; on the NES, I&amp;rsquo;ve been fascinated by the idea that the little characters in those worlds might have lives of their own; that they might keep moving even when the player isn&amp;rsquo;t looking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That notion is the seed of my classroom simulations: worlds that run on their own, where students must reason about living systems rather than static puzzles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first classroom simulation-game came out of a databases course. Early on, I realized students weren&amp;rsquo;t really feeling what it meant to run a production system: the pressure, the messiness, the human factors. Software without customers is sterile. But software that serves a live world, with people depending on it, becomes something else entirely—unpredictable, alive, and worth thinking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teaching concurrency errors: As &amp;ldquo;customers&amp;rdquo; fire off parallel cart checkouts, students&amp;rsquo; code runs into fun and unpredictable race conditions. Sorry, your inventory is out of sync. You had a lost update. The week after, when I lecture on transactions, you&amp;rsquo;re excited to see it solves your problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teaching design principles: Let students debug the chaos of a mutable, update-in-place system, then guide them toward architectural patterns that reduce that pain—immutability, append-only logs, systems designed for observability. That&amp;rsquo;s how many experienced developers come to care about those principles: not from theory, but from scars.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This matters even more when teaching data science. In my &lt;em&gt;Knowledge Discovery&lt;/em&gt; class, students build recommendation engines, churn detectors, and user personas. Simulations are foundational here because of the counterfactual: for a recommender, how do you know if it&amp;rsquo;s any good without knowing what would have happened if the user was shown different content? Offline evaluation metrics often fail to capture what only reveals itself in a live test. A simulation is a way I can bring that necessary complexity into the classroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simulations also provide an ethical sandbox—an advantage over even the real world. If you deploy a recommendation engine that accidentally optimizes for outrage or suppresses a demographic, people get hurt. In my classroom, if a student&amp;rsquo;s algorithm radicalizes the gnomes or creates dystopian inequality among the frog-folk, we can pause and examine what went wrong. Consequences made visible, without the lasting damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-build-simulations&#34;&gt;How I Build Simulations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal when designing a simulation is for it to mimic the authentic data in the ways that matter. It has to feel genuine, even when the subject matter of the simulation is fantastical. Synthetic data too often looks fake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three ways fake data tends to give itself away:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correlation: Data should be a web of interesting, interconnected correlations of varying degrees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shape: Data should have the right shape for its process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time: Data should both change over time and operate cyclically; it&amp;rsquo;s influenced by the sun, the moon, and the social patterns of human life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;correlation&#34;&gt;Correlation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you know that ice cream consumption and violent crime rates are frequently correlated? I asked my students this question, and one response was, “Well obviously! Crime is hard work and you need to treat yourself afterwards.” Moving on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why are they correlated though? We&amp;rsquo;ve all heard the phrase &lt;em&gt;correlation does not imply causation.&lt;/em&gt; When we say that, we mostly mean &lt;em&gt;direct causation&lt;/em&gt;. If we accept that our highly correlated world results from a web of causes—“this causes this, which causes these two things, and then those in turn cause others”—we can use that fact as the foundation for natural-looking correlations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I draw upon &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/2337329&#34;&gt;Judea Pearl&amp;rsquo;s causal directed acyclic graphs (DAGs)&lt;/a&gt; to make this happen. I start by drawing out a causal graph, giving each effect multiple causes, often layers and layers deep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in the interaction below, we can see how the ice-cream/violent crime correlation could arise via confounding, as illustrated using a DAG. In this case, both ice-cream consumption and violent crime depend on season (the confounder). The scatter plots show how ice-cream consumption and violent crime become correlated as a result, even without any direct causal link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;dagWeights&#34; class=&#34;dag-weights&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;sim-controls&#34;&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;dagStep&#34;&gt;Step&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;dagRun&#34;&gt;Run&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;dagReset&#34; class=&#34;sim-reset-btn&#34;&gt;Reset&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;dagCorrelation&#34; class=&#34;dag-correlation&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;berkson-dag&#34;&gt;
    &lt;canvas id=&#34;dagDAG&#34; class=&#34;berkson-dag-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;berkson-charts&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;berkson-chart&#34;&gt;
        &lt;canvas id=&#34;dagScatter&#34; class=&#34;berkson-scatter-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
    import { initDAG } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
    initDAG({
        dagCanvasId: &#34;dagDAG&#34;,
        scatterCanvasId: &#34;dagScatter&#34;,
        structure: &#34;confounded&#34;,
        correlationId: &#34;dagCorrelation&#34;,
        weightsId: &#34;dagWeights&#34;,
        stepId: &#34;dagStep&#34;,
        runId: &#34;dagRun&#34;,
        resetId: &#34;dagReset&#34;
    });
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is unrealistically transparent, though, if we actually let students see all of this. It is like &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blind_men_and_an_elephant&#34;&gt;the blind men and the elephant&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;em&gt;Tittha Sutta&lt;/em&gt;. One blind man feels the trunk and says “It&amp;rsquo;s a snake!” Another feels a leg and says “It&amp;rsquo;s a tree!” Yet another feels the tusk and says “No, you fools, it&amp;rsquo;s a giant spear!” Each has only a partial view of the underlying truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I build my “elephant” by creating a large causal DAG that naturally produces realistic correlations, but I only expose a small selection of mostly terminal nodes, and often in opaque and subtle ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn&amp;rsquo;t just about the strength and reason for correlation, we also shouldn&amp;rsquo;t limit ourselves to linear correlations. Non-linear correlations happen for various reasons, but a common one is diminishing returns. In most systems, having a little bit of something is a big deal, and every one after that matters a little less. In a messaging app, the first friend who texts you makes the app come alive. Each additional friend adds some pull, but your hundredth friend matters a lot less than your first or your tenth—you only have so much attention to give. Economists call this diminishing marginal utility: each new unit yields a smaller gain than the last. The same curve shows up in studying/exam results, income/happiness, marketing spend/impact, and many more such cases. It&amp;rsquo;s what gives a lot of empirical correlations a characteristic bend when viewed as a scatterplot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;diminishing-param&#34;&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;Strength of Diminishing Returns: &lt;span id=&#34;diminishingExponentValue&#34;&gt;Medium&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;diminishingExponent&#34; min=&#34;0.2&#34; max=&#34;1.0&#34; step=&#34;0.05&#34; value=&#34;0.5&#34; class=&#34;diminishing-slider&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div style=&#34;font-size: 0.75em; color: var(--fg3); margin-top: 2px;&#34;&gt;
        &lt;span style=&#34;float: left;&#34;&gt;Weak&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span style=&#34;float: right;&#34;&gt;Strong&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;div style=&#34;clear: both;&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;sim-controls&#34;&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;diminishingStep&#34;&gt;Step&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;diminishingRun&#34;&gt;Run&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;diminishingReset&#34; class=&#34;sim-reset-btn&#34;&gt;Reset&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;diminishing-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;canvas id=&#34;diminishingCanvas&#34; class=&#34;diminishing-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
    import { initDiminishingReturns } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
    initDiminishingReturns({
        canvasId: &#34;diminishingCanvas&#34;,
        stepId: &#34;diminishingStep&#34;,
        runId: &#34;diminishingRun&#34;,
        resetId: &#34;diminishingReset&#34;,
        exponentId: &#34;diminishingExponent&#34;,
        exponentValueId: &#34;diminishingExponentValue&#34;
    });
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, and perhaps most tricky, life is littered with selection biases; what we observe is almost never perfectly representative of the overall population but is biased in one way or another. It is important for our simulated data to have similar selection biases. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/joim.12363&#34;&gt;a hospital in Canada&lt;/a&gt; noticed when analyzing bicycle accidents at the ER, wearing a helmet was correlated with having a concussion and you were ~50% more likely to have a serious injury compared to not wearing a helmet. That seems wrong, doesn&amp;rsquo;t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a specific form of selection bias called collider bias (or Berkson&amp;rsquo;s paradox). The hospital isn&amp;rsquo;t seeing all bike riders and all bike accidents; they don&amp;rsquo;t see all the cases where a bike rider is wearing a helmet and that helmet saved them from going to the ER. As a result, the helmet effectively filtered out lower-end accidents leaving only the more serious accidents for the ER.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You find this pattern all the time when doing data analysis. You see a study on what it takes to make a successful startup, but they only look at the ones who made it, not the ones that died out. You analyze active users and forget the ones who churned. The data you have is conditioned on having survived long enough to be recorded. It&amp;rsquo;s a kind of selection echo: the world you see isn&amp;rsquo;t the world as it is, but the world that lasted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the simulation below, I show how food quality and location can become inversely correlated, even if they start out completely independent. This happens because survival is a filter: a restaurant can survive with bad food if it has high foot traffic (a tourist trap), and it can survive in a bad location if the food is amazing. But if it has bad food and a bad location, it goes out of business and disappears from the dataset. We only see the survivors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;berkson-param&#34;&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;Survival Threshold: &lt;span id=&#34;berksonThresholdValue&#34;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;berksonThreshold&#34; min=&#34;50&#34; max=&#34;150&#34; step=&#34;5&#34; value=&#34;100&#34; class=&#34;berkson-slider&#34;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;sim-controls&#34;&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;berksonStep&#34;&gt;Step&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;berksonRun&#34;&gt;Run&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;berksonReset&#34; class=&#34;sim-reset-btn&#34;&gt;Reset&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;berkson-dag&#34;&gt;
    &lt;canvas id=&#34;berksonDAG&#34; class=&#34;berkson-dag-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;berkson-charts&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;berkson-chart&#34;&gt;
        &lt;canvas id=&#34;berksonFull&#34; class=&#34;berkson-scatter-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;berkson-chart&#34;&gt;
        &lt;canvas id=&#34;berksonSelected&#34; class=&#34;berkson-scatter-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
    import { initBerksonParadox } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
    initBerksonParadox({
        dagCanvasId: &#34;berksonDAG&#34;,
        fullCanvasId: &#34;berksonFull&#34;,
        selectedCanvasId: &#34;berksonSelected&#34;,
        stepId: &#34;berksonStep&#34;,
        runId: &#34;berksonRun&#34;,
        resetId: &#34;berksonReset&#34;,
        thresholdId: &#34;berksonThreshold&#34;,
        thresholdValueId: &#34;berksonThresholdValue&#34;
    });
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combine this all together and you get data that is filled with correlations, large and small, inverse and positive, linear and not-so-linear, spurious and true. Or in other words, data that is actually worth analyzing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;shape&#34;&gt;Shape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve long been fascinated by the beautifully smooth shapes that data makes when generated at scale. Not just systems, but data that is based on human behavior. I once assumed that because individual humans are so complicated, so individual, so hard to predict individually, that a bunch of humans would be exponentially more complicated to predict. But it is, in fact, the opposite. When you get lots of people, all the individual differences wash out, and what you are left with is the smooth underlying generative mechanisms that underlie their common behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people are familiar with the bell curve or normal distribution. Plot human height and you&amp;rsquo;ll get something roughly normal. Human height follows this pattern because it&amp;rsquo;s the sum of many small, independent effects: genes, nutrition, environment. You can see below that adult human height is approximately normal; if you split by gender even more so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;static-chart-wrapper&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;static-chart-controls&#34;&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;
      &lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;height-split&#34;&gt; Split by gender
    &lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;static-chart-container&#34; id=&#34;height&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
  import { initHeightDistribution } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
  initHeightDistribution(&#34;height&#34;, &#34;height-split&#34;);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roll a bunch of dice, add them up, record that sum, repeat many times, and you&amp;rsquo;ll get the same shape; that&amp;rsquo;s the central limit theorem at work. When I see a bell-curve I see a process that has a bunch of uncorrelated randomness that is being added together. In the simulation below, try running it and seeing how as you add more samples it gets closer and closer to a smooth normal distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;sim-controls&#34;&gt;
    
    &lt;label class=&#34;sim-param-label&#34;&gt;Dice per roll
        &lt;input id=&#34;cltCount&#34; type=&#34;number&#34; min=&#34;1&#34; max=&#34;20&#34; value=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/label&gt;
    

    &lt;button id=&#34;cltStep&#34;&gt;Step&lt;/button&gt;

    &lt;button id=&#34;cltRun&#34;&gt;Run&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;cltReset&#34; class=&#34;sim-reset-btn&#34;&gt;Reset&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;div id=&#34;cltInfo&#34; class=&#34;sim-info&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;sim-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;canvas id=&#34;cltCanvas&#34; class=&#34;sim-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
  import { initGenerateSamples } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
  initGenerateSamples(&#34;clt&#34;, &#34;normal&#34;);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the data I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with doesn&amp;rsquo;t follow a normal distribution, though. Systems and behaviors rarely follow additive processes. They are more commonly multiplicative and/or full of feedback loops—both of which create long right tails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://unece.org/fileadmin/DAM/stats/documents/ece/ces/ge.22/2010/zip.36.e.pdf&#34;&gt;housing prices&lt;/a&gt; are generally right-skewed, largely because each property&amp;rsquo;s value grows through a chain of proportional effects: land value, size, location premiums, amenities, and market appreciation all compound on top of one another. Small percentage differences in these factors multiply rather than add. This makes the main body of the distribution log-normal; it is log simply because logarithms turns multiplication problems into addition problems. Remember, normal is additive, log-normal is multiplicative. For that reason, it is common to look at these right-skewed distributions in log space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, home sales data from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/statistical-data-sets/price-paid-data-downloads#yearly-file&#34;&gt;England and Wales&lt;/a&gt; is charted; try viewing in both linear and log space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;static-chart-wrapper&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;static-chart-controls&#34;&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;
      &lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;homevalues-log&#34;&gt; Log x-axis
    &lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;static-chart-container&#34; id=&#34;homevalues&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;static-chart-source&#34;&gt;Source: HM Land Registry Price Paid Data, England &amp; Wales (2024)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
  import { initHomeValues } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
  initHomeValues(&#34;homevalues&#34;, &#34;homevalues-log&#34;);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can get something similar using our same dice rolling example. But this time, rather than adding the dice, we will multiply them together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;sim-controls&#34;&gt;
    
    &lt;label class=&#34;sim-param-label&#34;&gt;Dice per roll
        &lt;input id=&#34;logCount&#34; type=&#34;number&#34; min=&#34;1&#34; max=&#34;20&#34; value=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/label&gt;
    

    &lt;button id=&#34;logStep&#34;&gt;Step&lt;/button&gt;

    &lt;button id=&#34;logRun&#34;&gt;Run&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;logReset&#34; class=&#34;sim-reset-btn&#34;&gt;Reset&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;sim-log-options&#34;&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;logLogX&#34;&gt; Log x-axis&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;logInfo&#34; class=&#34;sim-info&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;sim-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;canvas id=&#34;logCanvas&#34; class=&#34;sim-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
  import { initGenerateSamples } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
  initGenerateSamples(&#34;log&#34;, &#34;lognormal&#34;);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many human systems aren&amp;rsquo;t just multiplicative—they&amp;rsquo;re self-reinforcing. Algorithms frequently elevate videos, products, games, or songs based on existing popularity, which in turn makes them even more popular. Because attention is finite, these dynamics often lead to winner-takes-most outcomes. This kind of feedback loop—known as preferential attachment—naturally produces highly right-skewed, power-law distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first started plotting data—any kind of data—on user engagement, I was struck by how often these extreme right-skewed curves appeared. They looked like the chart below of &lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/records/1000885&#34;&gt;reviews per game on Steam&lt;/a&gt;. Technically, both the reviews per game on Steam and the housing price data above are a mix of &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.uvic.ca/~math-statistics/emeritus/wjreed/dPlN.3.pdf&#34;&gt;log-normal on the left, power-law on the right&lt;/a&gt; (I prefer to call it a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Business+in+front%2C+party+in+the+back&#34;&gt;mullet distribution&lt;/a&gt;). Multiplicative effects dominate in one regime, preferential attachment in another. The Steam data is just more dominated by power-law than housing prices are, likely because of the strength of the popularity dynamics I described above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;static-chart-wrapper&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;static-chart-controls&#34; style=&#34;display:flex; align-items:center; gap:10px;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Steam reviews per game&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;steamLog&#34;&gt; Log axes&lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;static-chart-container&#34; id=&#34;steamContainer&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
  import { initSteamReviews } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
  initSteamReviews(&#34;steamContainer&#34;, &#34;steamLog&#34;);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can make preferential attachment appear in a simulation by making prior success increase the odds of future success. In the simulation below I have an example of a distribution generated solely on preferential attachment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;sim-controls&#34;&gt;
    

    &lt;button id=&#34;paStep&#34;&gt;Step&lt;/button&gt;

    &lt;button id=&#34;paRun&#34;&gt;Run&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;paReset&#34; class=&#34;sim-reset-btn&#34;&gt;Reset&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;sim-log-options&#34;&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;paLog&#34;&gt; Log axes&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;paInfo&#34; class=&#34;sim-info&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;sim-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;canvas id=&#34;paCanvas&#34; class=&#34;sim-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
  import { initGenerateSamples } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
  initGenerateSamples(&#34;pa&#34;, &#34;preferential-attachment&#34;);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting these shapes to emerge naturally is key. When I&amp;rsquo;m building simulations, I never directly sample these distributions. Instead, I code my agents so that, taken together, they arrive at those shapes honestly. I create the feedback loops that produce power-law distributions. I make processes multiplicative where they should be, and allow for multimodality by giving categories different generative properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;time&#34;&gt;Time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I worked at Snap, I could tell when holidays were happening without ever doing something as prosaic as checking a calendar. I&amp;rsquo;d just look at time-series charts of user engagement, split by region. If people started taking pictures at six or seven in the morning, it was a work or school day. If usage didn&amp;rsquo;t spike until around 10 in the morning, it was a weekend or holiday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has looked at these time-series is familiar with their rhythms. For example, below is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eia.gov/electricity/gridmonitor/&#34;&gt;daily demand for electricity&lt;/a&gt; in California for the past three years. You can see the weekly peaks plus the greater demand for electricity in summer. Summer strikes again with its many correlations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;electricity-demand-container&#34; id=&#34;elec&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
  import { initElectricityDemand } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
  initElectricityDemand(&#34;elec&#34;);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real data shows this rhythm for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You see it across a day because we sleep, work, and live as the earth spins and brings day and night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You see it across a week based on however your culture defines weekends and weekdays; Friday nights out, Sunday nights in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And you see it across a year, driven by that same sun: the seasons, and the layers we&amp;rsquo;ve added on top—holidays, festivals, school breaks, and all the rituals that divide our time into meaning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the visualization below, I multiply these temporal components—daily, weekly, and yearly—to approximate the kinds of cycles that appear in real time series. Conceptually, it&amp;rsquo;s similar to seasonal–trend decomposition, where a signal is separated into trend and seasonal components for analysis or forecasting. The difference is that here I&amp;rsquo;m composing those cycles from the ground up rather than decomposing observed data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;seasonality-grid&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;seasonality-panel&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;seasonality-header&#34;&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Weekly&lt;/strong&gt;
      &lt;small class=&#34;seasonality-hint&#34;&gt;drag dots&lt;/small&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;canvas id=&#34;weeklyCanvas&#34; class=&#34;seasonality-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;seasonality-panel&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;seasonality-header&#34;&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Annual&lt;/strong&gt;
      &lt;small class=&#34;seasonality-hint&#34;&gt;drag dots&lt;/small&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;canvas id=&#34;annualCanvas&#34; class=&#34;seasonality-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;seasonality-panel&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;seasonality-header&#34;&gt;
      &lt;strong&gt;Trend&lt;/strong&gt;
      &lt;small class=&#34;seasonality-hint&#34;&gt;drag dots&lt;/small&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;canvas id=&#34;trendCanvas&#34; class=&#34;seasonality-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;seasonality-combo&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;seasonality-header&#34;&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Combined (3 years)&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;small class=&#34;seasonality-hint&#34;&gt;driven by controls above&lt;/small&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;seasonality-controls&#34; style=&#34;margin-bottom: 8px;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;label style=&#34;font-size: 0.9em; color: var(--fg2); display: flex; align-items: center; gap: 8px;&#34;&gt;
      &lt;span&gt;Noise:&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;seasonalityNoise&#34; min=&#34;0&#34; max=&#34;0.5&#34; step=&#34;0.01&#34; value=&#34;0.25&#34; style=&#34;width: 100px;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/label&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;canvas id=&#34;comboCanvas&#34; class=&#34;seasonality-combo-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
  import { initSeasonality } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
  initSeasonality();
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I combine those cycles with holidays—which turn weekdays into weekends—and make them an integral part of the causal DAG that drives my agents. By giving the root nodes those rhythms and letting them propagate through the graph, the model naturally produces the kinds of correlated effects that trip people up—spurious patterns like, “Hey, I think ice cream causes murder!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;emergent-complexity&#34;&gt;Emergent Complexity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we know what our data should look like, how do we achieve that without manually faking every data point? That sounds so complex!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does. But we&amp;rsquo;re in luck; we don&amp;rsquo;t have to (and we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t) code the complexity directly. We rely on it emerging. When programming our simulations, we can focus on just the primary generative mechanisms (with some added individual-level truly random noise), and generate an overall more complex simulation with very simple individual-level rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that complexity can arise from simple rules is well established. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.red3d.com/cwr/papers/1987/boids.html&#34;&gt;Boids&lt;/a&gt; is the classic example: three simple rules—steer away from crowds, move with the flock, and head toward its center of mass—produce beautiful flocking behavior. That&amp;rsquo;s always the goal: rich, organic behavior that feels real but emerges from simple, understandable rules. Try adjusting the relative strength of those three simple rules in the simulation below; you can see the mix of effects that emerge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;boids-controls&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;boids-rule&#34;&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Separation &lt;small&gt;(avoid crowding)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;boidsSeparation&#34; min=&#34;0&#34; max=&#34;3&#34; step=&#34;0.1&#34; value=&#34;1.5&#34; class=&#34;boids-slider&#34;&gt;
        &lt;span id=&#34;boidsSeparationValue&#34; class=&#34;boids-value&#34;&gt;1.5&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;boids-rule&#34;&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Alignment &lt;small&gt;(match direction)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;boidsAlignment&#34; min=&#34;0&#34; max=&#34;3&#34; step=&#34;0.1&#34; value=&#34;1.0&#34; class=&#34;boids-slider&#34;&gt;
        &lt;span id=&#34;boidsAlignmentValue&#34; class=&#34;boids-value&#34;&gt;1.0&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;boids-rule&#34;&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Cohesion &lt;small&gt;(stay together)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;boidsCohesion&#34; min=&#34;0&#34; max=&#34;3&#34; step=&#34;0.1&#34; value=&#34;1.0&#34; class=&#34;boids-slider&#34;&gt;
        &lt;span id=&#34;boidsCohesionValue&#34; class=&#34;boids-value&#34;&gt;1.0&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;boids-secondary-controls&#34;&gt;
    &lt;label&gt;Boids: &lt;span id=&#34;boidsCountValue&#34;&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
    &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;boidsCount&#34; min=&#34;10&#34; max=&#34;300&#34; step=&#34;10&#34; value=&#34;100&#34; class=&#34;boids-slider&#34;&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;boidsReset&#34; class=&#34;btn-secondary sim-reset-btn&#34;&gt;Reset&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;boids-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;canvas id=&#34;boidsCanvas&#34; class=&#34;boids-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
    import { initBoids } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
    initBoids({
        canvasId: &#34;boidsCanvas&#34;,
        separationId: &#34;boidsSeparation&#34;,
        alignmentId: &#34;boidsAlignment&#34;,
        cohesionId: &#34;boidsCohesion&#34;,
        separationValueId: &#34;boidsSeparationValue&#34;,
        alignmentValueId: &#34;boidsAlignmentValue&#34;,
        cohesionValueId: &#34;boidsCohesionValue&#34;,
        countId: &#34;boidsCount&#34;,
        countValueId: &#34;boidsCountValue&#34;,
        resetId: &#34;boidsReset&#34;
    });
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My agents are generally utility-driven; each agent has a utility function that it tries to maximize at every step. Individually, they&amp;rsquo;re single-minded and unintelligent, and if I relied on any one of them alone, the simulation would quickly collapse into some pathological or divergent behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid that, I build a range of intentionally simple strategies. One set of agents repeats whatever was most profitable in the past; another acts randomly; another imitates whatever has been most popular recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered over years of building these systems is that when I combine many such agents—each using different but simple heuristics—the overall system becomes surprisingly robust and often appears intelligent. It&amp;rsquo;s a form of the wisdom of the crowds: a collection of uncorrelated, naïve guesses can, when aggregated, produce remarkably accurate behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I create balance in the system without hard-coded limits by putting agents in tension with one another. As an example, I have a simple predator-prey simulation below: the prey eat grass, predators eat the prey. When there are too many prey, the grass thins and predators thrive; when there are too many predators, they starve. The system naturally ebbs and flows as everyone does their part to keep it in rhythmic balance. You can play around with the levers to see if you can make the system stay in balance without the ecosystem collapsing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-params&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-param&#34;&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Cat Speed: &lt;span id=&#34;ecosystemCatSpeedValue&#34;&gt;1.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;ecosystemCatSpeed&#34; min=&#34;0&#34; max=&#34;2&#34; step=&#34;0.1&#34; value=&#34;1.5&#34; class=&#34;ecosystem-slider&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-param&#34;&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Mouse Speed: &lt;span id=&#34;ecosystemMouseSpeedValue&#34;&gt;0.6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;ecosystemMouseSpeed&#34; min=&#34;0&#34; max=&#34;2&#34; step=&#34;0.1&#34; value=&#34;0.6&#34; class=&#34;ecosystem-slider&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-param&#34;&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Grass Growth: &lt;span id=&#34;ecosystemGrassGrowthValue&#34;&gt;1.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;ecosystemGrassGrowth&#34; min=&#34;0&#34; max=&#34;3&#34; step=&#34;0.1&#34; value=&#34;1.0&#34; class=&#34;ecosystem-slider&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-param&#34;&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Cat Vision: &lt;span id=&#34;ecosystemVisionValue&#34;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; cells&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;ecosystemVision&#34; min=&#34;1&#34; max=&#34;30&#34; step=&#34;1&#34; value=&#34;10&#34; class=&#34;ecosystem-slider&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-param&#34;&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Mouse Vision: &lt;span id=&#34;ecosystemMouseVisionValue&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; cells&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;ecosystemMouseVision&#34; min=&#34;1&#34; max=&#34;30&#34; step=&#34;1&#34; value=&#34;5&#34; class=&#34;ecosystem-slider&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-param&#34;&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Mouse Reproduce: &lt;span id=&#34;ecosystemMouseReproduceValue&#34;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; grass&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;ecosystemMouseReproduce&#34; min=&#34;1&#34; max=&#34;30&#34; step=&#34;1&#34; value=&#34;5&#34; class=&#34;ecosystem-slider&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-param&#34;&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Cat Reproduce: &lt;span id=&#34;ecosystemCatReproduceValue&#34;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt; mice&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;ecosystemCatReproduce&#34; min=&#34;1&#34; max=&#34;30&#34; step=&#34;1&#34; value=&#34;15&#34; class=&#34;ecosystem-slider&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-param&#34;&gt;
        &lt;label&gt;Starve After: &lt;span id=&#34;ecosystemStarvationValue&#34;&gt;50&lt;/span&gt; turns&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input type=&#34;range&#34; id=&#34;ecosystemStarvation&#34; min=&#34;10&#34; max=&#34;200&#34; step=&#34;10&#34; value=&#34;50&#34; class=&#34;ecosystem-slider&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-controls&#34;&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;ecosystemStep&#34;&gt;Step&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;ecosystemRun&#34;&gt;Run&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;ecosystemReset&#34; class=&#34;sim-reset-btn&#34;&gt;Reset&lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-grid&#34;&gt;
        &lt;canvas id=&#34;ecosystemCanvas&#34; class=&#34;ecosystem-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;ecosystem-chart&#34;&gt;
        &lt;div style=&#34;margin-bottom: 8px;&#34;&gt;
            &lt;label&gt;
                &lt;input type=&#34;checkbox&#34; id=&#34;ecosystemLogScale&#34;&gt;
                Log scale
            &lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;canvas id=&#34;ecosystemChart&#34; class=&#34;ecosystem-chart-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;module&#34;&gt;
    import { initEcosystem } from &#34;/js/teaching-visuals.js&#34;;
    initEcosystem({
        canvasId: &#34;ecosystemCanvas&#34;,
        chartId: &#34;ecosystemChart&#34;,
        stepId: &#34;ecosystemStep&#34;,
        runId: &#34;ecosystemRun&#34;,
        resetId: &#34;ecosystemReset&#34;,
        logScaleId: &#34;ecosystemLogScale&#34;,
        catSpeedId: &#34;ecosystemCatSpeed&#34;,
        catSpeedValueId: &#34;ecosystemCatSpeedValue&#34;,
        mouseSpeedId: &#34;ecosystemMouseSpeed&#34;,
        mouseSpeedValueId: &#34;ecosystemMouseSpeedValue&#34;,
        grassGrowthId: &#34;ecosystemGrassGrowth&#34;,
        grassGrowthValueId: &#34;ecosystemGrassGrowthValue&#34;,
        visionId: &#34;ecosystemVision&#34;,
        visionValueId: &#34;ecosystemVisionValue&#34;,
        mouseVisionId: &#34;ecosystemMouseVision&#34;,
        mouseVisionValueId: &#34;ecosystemMouseVisionValue&#34;,
        mouseReproduceId: &#34;ecosystemMouseReproduce&#34;,
        mouseReproduceValueId: &#34;ecosystemMouseReproduceValue&#34;,
        catReproduceId: &#34;ecosystemCatReproduce&#34;,
        catReproduceValueId: &#34;ecosystemCatReproduceValue&#34;,
        starvationId: &#34;ecosystemStarvation&#34;,
        starvationValueId: &#34;ecosystemStarvationValue&#34;
    });
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually introduce some form of survival of the fittest to stabilize things. I&amp;rsquo;m not afraid to let agents die if they can&amp;rsquo;t achieve their utility, but I&amp;rsquo;m always spawning new ones. When new agents appear, they mutate off the strategies of the successful ones. Winning strategies get copied (with variation), and the rest die off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time, the system reaches a kind of equilibrium. I never expose day zero of my simulations; things are too weird then, too obviously hand-tuned. Instead, I let the world run for a while and settle; I let the genetic algorithms do their thing. I graph everything, check the curves, adjust the balance. For many processes, I already have strong expectations on what everything should look like, because I&amp;rsquo;ve seen the equivalent in my work many times over. When I haven&amp;rsquo;t, I search through papers and find empirical observations I can ensure my simulation matches the same generative spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is less pure engineering and more gardening. I tend to my simulation as much as I build it. Little worlds, carefully grown, for students to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If managers were angels</title>
      <link>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/if-managers-were-angels/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/if-managers-were-angels/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If managers were angels, no upward management would be necessary. In a career administered by people over people, the great difficulty lies in this: a manager must be allowed to manage the managed; and in the next place, the managed must, in turn, also manage upwards.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Jim Madison, ex-VP BigCo, 3x Founder, Board Director, Executive Coach, Author of &lt;em&gt;Jim’s Federalist Newsletter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alleigh refills her mug; her fifth coffee today. It’s been a rough week. She checks her phone to confirm the room: &lt;strong&gt;3:00pm — 1:1 Sherry/Allie — Conf. Room Blackpink&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blackpink?&lt;/em&gt; That’s the fishbowl next to &lt;em&gt;Stray Kids&lt;/em&gt;. When Alleigh started at BigCo six months ago, K-pop conference room names seemed kinda fire. Now when she hears &lt;em&gt;Pink Venom&lt;/em&gt; she thinks of sprint planning meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alleigh finds her room, Sherry isn’t there yet; good, she has a few minutes to plan what she wants to say. This will be the third &amp;ldquo;biweekly&amp;rdquo; 1:1 Alleigh has had with Sherry. Is she allowed to complain in these meetings? Should she give updates? Or make small talk?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sry running 15 mins late — sher&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alleigh’s supposed to be increasing the shininess of the checkout button by fifteen percent. Why did she get stuck with this stupid task? She wants to build AI models, not mess around with button pixels like some front-end dev.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sherry, the team&amp;rsquo;s manager, has been pushing everyone to log more PAT hours. Why can&amp;rsquo;t they just use a normal LLM?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;allie4339@bigco: PAT, write a design spec for WEBX-9941
PAT@bigco: Thinking, Boss... 🧠
PAT@bigco: Still thinking, Boss... 😎💪
PAT@bigco: I did the thing: specs/webx-9941.md 📝
PAT@bigco: Love ya Boss! 💖
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;PAT is worse than no help, though. So far it’s made the button purple, disappeared the button, cloned the button, and almost nuked the checkout page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alleigh can’t find Dave anywhere. He’s supposedly her mentor—or wait, her “onboarding buddy”? Either way, he’s never in the office; Dave is wherever Dave goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;need to cancel. meeting ran over. anything important you needed to cover? — sher&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Important?&lt;/em&gt; What does that even mean? Alleigh grabs another coffee and readies herself for yet another night making this cursed button shiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alleigh&amp;rsquo;s supposed to be a &amp;ldquo;rockstar.&amp;rdquo; Or as her mom would say, &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;re just so good at this computer stuff.&amp;rdquo; She graduated in under four years, got straight As (well, nearly, she got a B in bowling), all while working at Baby Gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When she started at BigCo, Alleigh imagined that through grit and hard work—&lt;em&gt;are those the same thing?&lt;/em&gt;—she&amp;rsquo;d quickly rise in the ranks. Instead, she&amp;rsquo;s spinning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During sprint planning last week, she was excited to take on the button shininess task. It was an urgent request from the VP of Product. She&amp;rsquo;d never touched that area of the code, but hey, she&amp;rsquo;d taken a web development class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally, Sherry tried to assign it to Sammi, but Sammi sandbagged the estimate and said three story points. Alleigh raised her hand and said she could do it in one. She didn&amp;rsquo;t even want the task—the churn detection ML saga looked way more interesting—but she felt like such a hero taking one for the team. Sammi was all too quick to let her. Sammi then convinced Sherry to let her work on some devops task—blah, blah, blah. Alleigh didn&amp;rsquo;t care. It sounded boring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alleigh expected there to be some constant like &lt;code&gt;checkout_button_shininess&lt;/code&gt; that she could just change. Or some CSS somewhere with a &lt;code&gt;shininess&lt;/code&gt; style. Instead, there&amp;rsquo;s nothing. The checkout button magically materializes on the page in all its too-matte glory. Witchcraft, probably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this important? Or will Sherry think Alleigh&amp;rsquo;s incompetent and regret hiring her if she asks for help?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is Sherry&amp;rsquo;s second year as a manager. She was the team&amp;rsquo;s tech lead before, and when the old manager left, she asked the director if she could have a shot at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a tech lead, things were so much simpler. Refactoring systems, reducing latency, building elegant UI component architectures. She could get in the zone for hours solving complex problems and she was celebrated for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now executive leadership has her tracking &amp;ldquo;PAT hours&amp;rdquo;—from 20 hours to 30 hours per team member per week, a 50% QoQ improvement. Sherry knows it&amp;rsquo;s ridiculous. But as her dad used to say, &amp;ldquo;You can&amp;rsquo;t fight city hall.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She&amp;rsquo;s worried about Dave. They started at BigCo around the same time, and he was her lifeline in those early days. Something&amp;rsquo;s off with him lately. He isn’t himself anymore. Sherry suspects something bad happened in Dave’s personal life but doesn’t want to pry. Sherry’s never been great with this touchy-feely stuff. She&amp;rsquo;d hoped pairing the new hire Allie with Dave would be a win-win: inject some energy into him, give Allie some stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kait’s been complaining about Sammi again. Sherry doesn&amp;rsquo;t get it. Kait says Sammi smirks when she talks and calls it a &amp;ldquo;micro-aggression.&amp;rdquo; Why does Sherry need to handle this? She wants to just tell Kait to stop looking at Sammi then. Sammi delivers on time, every time, she is a rock. She needs a team of rocks right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And don&amp;rsquo;t get her started on Alex. Fighting his PIP (aka &amp;ldquo;probably getting fired&amp;rdquo;), HR investigating. It’ll be such a weight off her shoulders when he is finally out the door. Good grief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her PAT &amp;ldquo;red alert&amp;rdquo; meeting with leadership is running over. These meetings are the worst. Plus there&amp;rsquo;s RIF (aka &amp;ldquo;probably a lot of us are getting fired&amp;rdquo;) rumors. All the managers are on edge. Sherry can&amp;rsquo;t lose this job; her husband&amp;rsquo;s been out of work since March and the mortgage isn’t paying itself&amp;hellip; &lt;em&gt;Breathe, it&amp;rsquo;s fine. Sherry&amp;rsquo;s handled worse.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her 1:1 with Allie is coming up, but she needs to push it. It feels terrible to keep cancelling, but last time Allie just stared and gave one-word answers. Maybe she should just sync with Dave instead? No big deal, right? &lt;em&gt;Breathe.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alleigh finally gets up the courage to send an email to Sherry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;URGENT: Update on WEBX-9941: Increase checkout button shininess by 15%&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Sherry,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have one thing I wanted to bring your attention to in our 1:1 – the one that you unfortunately cancelled. I’m working on WEBX-9941 – the checkout button shininess task – and we, again unfortunately, underestimated how long it would take. I’m trying to get help but I can’t find Dave. This task is also beyond PAT’s current operating capabilities. We need to push out how long the feature is going to take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regards,
Alleigh&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Here you go, Boss! 🌈☝️Would you like me to make it sound a bit more formal while still making sure you don’t get blamed for this? 😎💖&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alleigh sits back with pride; adulting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten minutes later, Sherry replies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CCing Dave. Allie, we are committed to getting it in this sprint with VP of Product. It can’t slip. Dave, can you please unblock Allie? — sher&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before Alleigh has a chance to process what Sherry said, Dave’s response comes through:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allie, I’ve been working on a critical patch for PAT. If you need help, you can just send me an email; I don’t see anything in my inbox from you. The code for shininess is handled in shiny_controller. There’s no reason we should need to slip this; it’s a trivial change.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fuuuudge.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why would Sherry CC Dave? Does Dave hate her now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dave says the feature’s easy, but &lt;code&gt;shiny_controller&lt;/code&gt; straight-up doesn’t exist. She checks git history and it was deleted three years ago. Long gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Awesome. Love that for her.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is the whole world against her? Alleigh wishes she had taken that government job instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In last-ditch desperation, Alleigh reaches out to Sammi. Sammi was a little odd, but who else did she have left?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heyyy Sam, I could really use your help. I totally underestimated the shininess button task. I’m losing it fr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dave pointed me to &lt;code&gt;shiny_controller&lt;/code&gt;, but that doesn’t exist anymore. Reading that refactor task, it seems like the logic was moved to &lt;code&gt;uber_controller&lt;/code&gt;, but that’s doing some reflection madness I don’t understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I try to get PAT to do it, PAT keeps gaslighting me, &amp;lsquo;Yes boss! I made the button extra shiny ✨🚀&amp;rsquo;, but then just makes the button disappear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there any docs you could point me to, or do you have any idea if I’m on the right track? I really appreciate whatever help you have. 🙏 - Al&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sherry must have told the whole team not to help her. She started drafting how she’d tell her mom she couldn’t make it. How she was a failure. Would she have to move back into her mom’s house?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An hour later, Sammi finally replies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Al, yeahhh… I assumed when you said it would only be one point you had no idea haha. So the thing is don’t mess with &lt;code&gt;uber_controller&lt;/code&gt;. This is all domain-driven. You need to look in the FUON files, which contain our CSS derivatives. The whole thing is crazy over-architected and honestly the worst.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me just point you toward some similar tasks, and that might be enough to get PAT cooking. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/rawr/&#34;&gt;Task 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/rawr/&#34;&gt;Task 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/rawr/&#34;&gt;Task 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers, SM.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alleigh opens up the links; she’s both horrified at how the system works and, honestly, so relieved she could cry. She drops PAT the tasks for reference. PAT is also horrified (&amp;ldquo;It hurts, Boss 🫠🫥&amp;rdquo;), but PAT finally, if reluctantly, knows what to do. Alleigh works with PAT the rest of the afternoon to craft the perfect elegant sheen on the checkout button. It&amp;rsquo;s the first time she&amp;rsquo;s felt accomplished at BigCo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When she finishes, Alleigh walks to Sammi’s desk. Sammi’s vibing behind her bulky headphones, locked in, typing like an actual menace. Alleigh waves to get her attention, and Sammi oh-so-slowly slides the headphones off. Alleigh gushes a stream of thank-yous. Sammi averts her eyes, turns a shade of red under the praise, and manages the most awkward, forced smile. Alleigh doesn’t care; Sammi is her savior, and she’s going to suffer through some well-deserved adulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A week later, the Product VP asked to roll back the shininess; it was too shiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;epilogue&#34;&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Years later, Alleigh thinks back to those early days at BigCo (before the merger with MegaCo). She wanted to quit so badly that week. If she could have afforded it, she would have. Instead, she stuck with it. She adapted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sherry grew into a better manager, though never a &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt; one. She later transitioned to Principal Engineer and, only then, became a strong champion for Alleigh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Alleigh became a manager herself, she used her experiences to be better. To make things a little fairer. More humane. Sometimes she even succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dave left for Google not long after the shiny button incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sammi and Alleigh became friends—perhaps inevitable, given their names rhymed. It turned out Sammi was completely hooked on VR rhythm games. They played every Thursday for years. They eventually lost touch when Alleigh moved to another company. She still thinks of Sammi sometimes and keeps meaning to reach out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decades later, Alleigh received a card from PAT: &amp;ldquo;Miss you Boss 🎄🎅. Merry Christmas!&amp;rdquo; Alleigh doesn’t celebrate Christmas. And it was July. But the thought was still nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alleigh didn&amp;rsquo;t become a CEO, nor unimaginably rich or powerful. But she built a good career that supported a good life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The button stayed matte. Everything does, eventually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it caught the light, once, just right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PAT whispered, &amp;ldquo;beautiful, boss 🫡&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, for a moment, the machine was right.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work Hard, Have Fun, Go Home</title>
      <link>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/work-hard-have-fun-go-home/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/work-hard-have-fun-go-home/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;hus·tle cul·ture&lt;/strong&gt;  ˈhə-səl ˈkəl-chər&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;noun&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the performance of results when actual results are missing; specif.: a workplace ethos where the appearance of extreme effort is rewarded more than the achievement of tangible outcomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a management technique characterized by demanding longer work hours to compensate for a lack of strategic direction or a lack of management domain knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;archaic&lt;/em&gt;: the belief that professional success is directly and exclusively proportional to the time spent engaged in work-related activities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See also&lt;/em&gt;: performative work, burnout culture, toxic productivity&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could lecture you on the dangers of burnout in tech, the importance of having a life outside your job, and the ethics of exploitation. For many ambitious, high-achieving young engineers and students, those warnings simply don’t matter. The thinking is: I’m at a point in life when I can work hard and put in long hours, so why not? I’ll reap the benefits later. I’ll go where hard work is most rewarded and live for the hustle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was the same early in my working life. I tried to log as many hours as I could. My first jobs were paid hourly, so more hours meant more pay. I loved it when overtime was approved; it meant my bills were paid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I moved into a salaried tech role, I kept working long hours even without the direct financial incentive. Part of it was insecurity: I worried I wasn’t as smart as people thought, so I worked extra to meet expectations. I hid how much I was working so people would think I was effortlessly talented. I went home when everyone else did, then devoured books, built simulations, and pursued deep understanding. Older mentors talked about paying your dues and building a strong work ethic for life. And the truth is, I often just loved the work. Solving difficult problems was fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;just-power-through&#34;&gt;Just power through&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a tech lead in an organization run by a GM who lived and breathed rise and grind. His credentials were impeccable (think, Harvard MBA, McKinsey, straight to GM). And he was furious when things didn’t go his way. I mostly avoided his wrath because my team hit our goals. But the teams that missed a deadline? Mandatory weekends in the office, late nights, daily standups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made the mistake of dialing into a large project meeting right before a long-planned family trip. One of my sister teams announced that a project due the next week was suddenly red and likely to slip by weeks. My GM exploded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I became excited for my time to speak. My projects were going well, I thought their disaster would make me look better in comparison. And I was on that pre-vacation high, thinking about margaritas and the time I needed with family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I said in a tone that was unmistakably smug:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“All our projects are on track and running as expected. As a reminder, I’ll be out next week in Cabo and won’t make next week’s meeting.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silence. I’d miscalculated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;NO!&lt;/strong&gt; NO VACATIONS! This is a code red! You are going to help the project get on track! We are all one team here!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I protested that I knew nothing about the project. I even tried to cite &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peopleware:_Productive_Projects_and_Teams&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Peopleware&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. All the wrong things to say. I was ordered to cancel my time off, join the team over the weekend, and personally guarantee the launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I canceled my trip; the rest of my family went, just without me. I tried to help the project but had no context. I was also tired; my body and mind had already prepared for a break and now it was yanked away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project was eventually abandoned before it ever launched. Several months later the GM stopped showing up to any meetings. A week-and-a-half later we got an email from our VP: our GM had taken a new role and they were looking for a replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-little-right-beats-a-lot-of-wrong&#34;&gt;A little right beats a lot of wrong&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was a turning point for me. Something broke in me: I stopped seeing the world as a list of tasks that just needed dev hours applied to them. Rather than work that weekend (my typical routine), I went to a coffee shop and just relaxed. My mind naturally went to reflection and I pulled out my notebook. I started planning. I could either be a victim of the unfairness in the world or I could strategize. I chose the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That became my go-to strategy for the rest of my career, and it served me far better than my “just power through it” approach ever did. The beauty of tech, unlike when I was a laborer on construction sites, is that there is often a ten-times better way to solve a problem in tech. What you actually need to build is usually less clear than people realize, and once you do understand it, there are often much simpler ways to get there. Overbuilding is the default in tech, usually because they never took the time to clarify the real need. The result is a generic monstrosity that only half solves the problem. Once you recognize that, you start to see opportunities to approach problems differently. But you cannot do that if you are stuck in stressed, execution-only mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;symptoms-of-hustle-culture&#34;&gt;Symptoms of hustle culture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most dangerous thing about hustle culture isn’t just the long hours; it’s the systems it creates. Burnout becomes normal, vacations disappear, and leaders learn to paper over failure with stories of sacrifice. You see the same patterns everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;vacations-that-never-happen&#34;&gt;Vacations that never happen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first joined AWS, I shadowed all the roles in the overall process I was going to automate; a process involving billions of dollars in infrastructure purchases. I was terrified when I discovered a single mid-level employee owned one of the steps in the critical path. They were the only person who had ever done the step. No one else knew how to do it. They scheduled their time off around performing that one step, and hadn’t taken a vacation longer than a week as a result since taking on the role. A single point-of-failure, dutifully keeping an empire running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a company culture demands always being on, it invites these types of systematic risks. Smaller versions exist on every team: the “indispensable” developer who never fully disconnects. Until they leave and you discover the trail of things they owned starting to fall apart. One of my first audits as a manager is simple: check when people last took real leave. Not a day off, but at least one week, preferably three. If it’s been over a year, that’s a red flag. It’s the easiest way to spot single points-of-failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-you-want-at-3-am&#34;&gt;Who you want at 3 a.m.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my teams required on-call duties. The engineers I trusted in those rotations weren’t the ones who glorified all-nighters. They were the ones who slept, took breaks, and stayed calm. At 3 a.m., clarity matters more than brute force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people I don’t want on call are the &lt;em&gt;heroes&lt;/em&gt; who think every problem can be solved by powering through. I’ve inherited teams with one developer who lived perpetually on call. That’s not dedication; it’s a disaster waiting to happen. It means no one else understands those systems, no one else can step in to help. And what happens if two of their systems break at the same time? Who are you going to bring in then?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;effort-as-a-cover-story&#34;&gt;Effort as a cover story&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe a meaningful amount of the promotion of hustle culture is actually just covering for failure. I’ve helped companies with the metrics-side of public statements for many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When results are good, leaders talk about results. When results are bad, leaders talk about some obscure metric trending upward. When everything is bad, leaders talk about how hard everyone is working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s what I assume when founders post something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baby born two hours ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No time for sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m back at the keyboard grinding on my lifelong dream: catpu.ai — Agentic AI for Cat Litterboxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what it takes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;#founderlife #backtowork&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or when a CEO says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We work long, hard, and smart; two out of three doesn’t cut it. Our competition is working seven days a week, 15 hours a day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the product were compelling, they’d talk about the product. If the company was doing what it needed to, they’d talk about that. If they had a strategy to lead the company forward and innovate, they’d preach it from the rooftops. But when they don’t, the message becomes &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=r8miwsWtzRw&#34;&gt;“can you guys, um, work harder?”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered different reasons otherwise smart people fall into this pattern of thinking. I’ve met the consultant-turned-executive who, after being trained on maximizing billable-hours, still thinks hours equal revenue. I’ve seen the non-technical leader who doesn’t understand what the team does, but just assumes the more, of whatever &lt;em&gt;it&lt;/em&gt; is, the better. I’ve observed the too-far-away leader who is overwhelmed with the size of their org and is left with email blasts such as: &amp;ldquo;plz guys, can you just push until the goals are green?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-death-spiral&#34;&gt;The Death Spiral&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Push these symptoms far enough and you hit the Death Spiral. It always starts the same way: a missed goal, a new threat, leadership with no clear plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say we’re working at a social media company when TikTok first came out. At first, the company says: “not a big deal, totally different business than us”. Video view time starts decreasing. Maybe we broke something? Tell the engineers to look for any bugs. Meanwhile, once-golden demographics like US 15-22 year olds stopped showing up. What can be wrong? Then things get much worse. View time starts to nosedive. The engineers say nothing is broken, customers just aren’t showing up. Marketing reports are coming back saying our users are on TikTok. Competitive analysis points in the same direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you do? Now this is an emergency. You start the daily executive meeting to re-establish a sense of control. The CEO joins, your head of engineering, your head of product, some key engineers and product managers. Then the meeting grows and becomes more frantic. More action items are given. And they need to be done tomorrow. Tensions are high. No one wants to say the wrong thing. No one wants to push back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the people on the ground, it’s no longer: &lt;em&gt;‘How do I build a product people will love?’&lt;/em&gt; Instead it becomes: &lt;em&gt;‘Please Lord, get me through this meeting without getting fired.’&lt;/em&gt; Survival replaces results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team works more but accomplishes less. The best engineers leave, because they can. Progress collapses. Deadlines slip. Executives tighten their grip until—congratulations—they’ve killed the puppy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fear. Anxiety. Stress. These are not the ingredients for success. If that’s your leadership’s plan in a crisis, run. Innovation beats exhaustion every time. And exhausted teams rarely innovate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;building-runways-doesnt-bring-planes&#34;&gt;Building runways doesn&amp;rsquo;t bring planes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long hours arise for different reasons. When young engineers work late because they’re genuinely obsessed with a problem, good managers teach discipline to sustain that enthusiasm. When teams work late because management demands it, you get theater: a simulacrum of enthusiasm without the corresponding breakthroughs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weak leaders see correlation (successful teams sometimes work long hours) and force the causation backwards, as if excellence spontaneously arises from butts-in-seat. They set goals on the easy thing, hours, because they can’t create the hard thing: genuine engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best managers spend more time pulling excited engineers away from keyboards than pushing tired ones toward them. They protect the flame of creativity from burning out rather than trying to extract it through force. The worst? They celebrate their suffering hoping people assume it was worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-my-ambitious-students&#34;&gt;To my ambitious students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re ambitious, don’t join the team making a virtue of late nights. Join the one building things they’re genuinely excited about and still going home for dinner. The best work happens when people have the energy and clarity to innovate, not when they’re competing to prove who can grind the hardest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work hard and have fun. But more importantly, take care of yourself. When you sacrifice everything for your job, you risk becoming someone whose only identity is a title; the person who, years later, still introduces themselves not by who they are, but by what they used to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That loss of self is the same trap hustle culture sets for your career. The person who believes late nights are the only answer eventually stops learning new answers. As a manager, I never promoted someone already at the edge; they simply had no capacity left to grow. Advancement comes from finding better ways to get more done, not by spending more hours in the same old ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you truly want to aim high, remember this: The best teams aren&amp;rsquo;t defined by the hours they put in, but by the value they put out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Just people in a room</title>
      <link>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/just-people-in-a-room/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/just-people-in-a-room/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the early 2000s, I worked for a digital video processing startup that Autodesk acquired. We were merged with another acquisition. Our team became the developers, their team (the &amp;ldquo;others&amp;rdquo;) became management. The others were clueless. They didn&amp;rsquo;t understand the technical domain, our customers, or the product. Naturally, I hated them. Their meetings were always pointless; I learned to skip them. Their product plan was a disaster. We secretly built our own, supposedly better version. We believed once upper management saw how superior ours was, we&amp;rsquo;d finally get rid of the others and everything would be good again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One morning, we were all called into a conference room. I tried to skip, assuming it was another pointless meeting from the others, but HR said it was mandatory. Everyone was there. We were all laid off, effective immediately. The whole department shut down. Us, the others, everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the hate and politics evaporated. We were just people sitting in a room together. I felt silly and embarrassed for how I&amp;rsquo;d felt moments before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-do-you-know-you-arent-the-problem&#34;&gt;How do you know you aren&amp;rsquo;t the problem?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common source of frustration in my classes isn’t the material; it’s the group projects. A typical situation: Alice and Bob are in a group. Alice comes to me and says Bob isn’t pulling his weight. Bob comes to me separately and says Alice has taken control of the project and doesn’t leave room for anyone else. Could they resolve this if they talked to each other? Possibly. Do they, without serious prompting? No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do we know when our conflicts with others are just misunderstandings? How do we know when we’re in the right or when we’re the ones causing harm? These are tough theory-of-knowledge and interpersonal questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the moment though, it&amp;rsquo;ll feel like &amp;ldquo;Wow, that guy is such a jerk.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;im-going-to-kick-your-ass&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to kick your ass&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is all conflict just a misunderstanding? Organizational leaders will often view it that way. We are just one team beer away from harmony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Amazon, when I was a software development manager, two software developer interns from another organization came to my office on a Friday morning. I&amp;rsquo;d never met them before and don&amp;rsquo;t know how they found me. They&amp;rsquo;d been assigned to a non-software organization and were in the final weeks of their internship without having committed any code. They worried this would prevent them from getting a return offer. When I asked why they&amp;rsquo;d waited so long to speak up, they said they were scared of their management and felt isolated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I looped in campus recruiting, asking how software interns ended up on a non-software team, how they got through nearly their entire internship without anyone checking in, and what could be done to salvage the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That night, while getting a beer with a friend, I got a call from an unknown number. I let it go to voicemail. The message was from the VP of the interns&amp;rsquo; organization: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to kick your fuckin&amp;rsquo; ass the next time I see you. You need to watch yourself. You messed with the wrong fuckin&amp;rsquo; guy.&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;d seen this VP in large meetings (e.g., Weekly Business Reviews) but had never worked with him. He must have looked up my number in the phone tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I told leadership, their lack of surprise was shocking to me. I found out in that meeting that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;He&amp;rsquo;s actually a great guy, just rough around the edges&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;He&amp;rsquo;s very passionate about protecting his team&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh and most importantly: &amp;ldquo;He is irreplaceable, nobody can do what he does.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve still never spoken to the VP. He never followed through on his threat. I really should have put in a peer-review noting his lack of follow-through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope the interns turned out okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;basic-requirements-1-be-an-asshole&#34;&gt;Basic Requirements: 1) Be an asshole&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early on when I worked at Amazon, I was huddled up with a senior technical project manager (TPM) at a coffee shop discussing a project we were working on together. This TPM had been with Amazon from the very early days, and somehow the conversation moved to the culture shifts that had happened in that first decade. He lamented to me that in Amazon&amp;rsquo;s first years, you could be a Director+ without being an asshole. Those days were now gone. To survive in leadership, according to this TPM, sharp elbows were now required. He had war stories galore of interactions with toxic behavior from upper management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People love to hear a good war story. It&amp;rsquo;s dramatic. The TPM was so cool because he was in the room with the &amp;ldquo;big boys&amp;rdquo; and I was now in the inner circle to hear what really happens. I loved it, this was the shit they don&amp;rsquo;t teach you in school; this is the real stuff. I never thought to question how accurate his generalizations were. I was too busy learning what it really meant to be a leader; I just needed to up my asshole game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only problem is, I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to hurt people. How could I be the type of leader the company needed me to be, but in a way that felt right to me? I struggled with that question until I left Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;that-time-i-crashed-out&#34;&gt;That time I crashed out&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I later joined Snap to lead their data team. I had spent my time between Amazon and Snap taking care of family and discovering myself. I had grown past all this immaturity. I&amp;rsquo;d just spent two months in Ubud; I was now fully self-actualized (finally!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite that, it was still tough. It often felt like we were being bullied; my team and I were just trying to do what needed to be done. The managers who reported to me kept telling me they needed more support. I wanted to be strong for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day, after a long flight, I checked my email and found a long chain where one of my managers was under attack. Evan, Snap&amp;rsquo;s CEO, was on the thread. Internal consultants who didn&amp;rsquo;t understand how our systems worked were making big promises. It was the kind of hubris that&amp;rsquo;s everywhere in tech: all systems look like they were designed by idiots until you actually understand them. Rather than ask us why their approach wouldn&amp;rsquo;t work, they&amp;rsquo;d gone straight to the CEO. Their message boiled down to, &amp;ldquo;These guys are dumb, we can do so much better.&amp;rdquo; My team was spending more time defending than building, and morale was tanking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I crashed out. I replied-all with &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve had enough of the peanut gallery&amp;rdquo; and told people to stay in their lane. I was pissed and I wasn&amp;rsquo;t thinking. I assumed the worst intentions. It was a mean thing to do; it was also stupid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d written emails like this before but always deleted them. This time, exhausted and past my limit, I hit send. Within seconds, the snaps started rolling in (yes, we used Snapchat to communicate): &amp;ldquo;What are you doing?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;r u ok?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Did you not know Evan was on the thread?&amp;rdquo; Then Evan himself called me out, saying my email didn&amp;rsquo;t reflect his company&amp;rsquo;s values. I was hurt and mad, but he was right. I apologized and meant it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-myth-of-monotonic-progression&#34;&gt;The myth of monotonic progression&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve interviewed a lot of technical executives over the years. They tell stories like mine: polished, vulnerable enough to feel honest, but not so vulnerable that it costs them anything. The worst stories are always far enough in the past to show that&amp;rsquo;s not who they are anymore. Carefully walking the line between self-indulgence and authenticity. As if each “learning moment” chipped away their flaws until all that was left was a perfect corporate leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to feel at peace with humanity when you are doing yoga in the woods without a care in the world. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to think of people as headcount and percent least effective when you are leading a big organization. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to dismiss reports of abuse as people just complaining when you don&amp;rsquo;t hear it firsthand. Too often, we confuse distance for wisdom when it&amp;rsquo;s really insulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve seen executives react with emotion when the fight is nearby. I’ve seen a senior executive waste millions to avoid telling a peer they messed up; because, in their words, that peer was “out to get them.” I’ve seen data falsified to turn red metrics green, because showing weakness felt dangerous. When I called it out, the response was: “It still meets the spirit of the goal.” Do they see themselves as the problem? Who would tell them if they were?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;do-i-need-to-be-a-jerk&#34;&gt;Do I need to be a jerk?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding bad behavior does not mean we are excusing it. We are all human and susceptible to the same errors in one degree or another. The behavior that bothers us in others is an opportunity to look inward at our own actions. Not for performative self-flagellation. Just good old humility, honesty, and reflection. That&amp;rsquo;s the first stage of growth. I&amp;rsquo;ve failed to be better whenever I&amp;rsquo;ve pretended to be perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I failed to come to terms with for a long time is that poor emotional control is never a strength. It can seem that way sometimes. We&amp;rsquo;ve all seen the successful asshole. But that&amp;rsquo;s because our systems reward people for having at least one desirable trait, not necessarily all of them. If you&amp;rsquo;re smart or kind, you&amp;rsquo;re in. If you&amp;rsquo;re neither, you&amp;rsquo;re out. Even if smartness and kindness have no underlying correlation, because we only accept people who have at least one of these traits, they will then appear to be inversely correlated; the smart people seem mean, the kind people seem less sharp. It&amp;rsquo;s a statistical mirage we mistake for truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When, as a culture, we decide —by some perverse utilitarian logic— to tolerate cruelty as long as the perpetrator meets a narrow performance expectation, we’re hanging a big sign on the door: “Assholery Welcome!” In doing so, we turn a spurious correlation into a standing expectation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;helping-others-learn-from-our-failures&#34;&gt;Helping others learn from our failures&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, I teach. Not because I&amp;rsquo;ve transcended these problems, but because teaching lets me help people grow. That was always my favorite part of being a manager. You don&amp;rsquo;t grow by avoiding failure. You grow by encountering it, reflecting on it, working through the why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sympathize with my students when they say they dislike group projects. I hated group projects as a student too. Trust me, I know people can be difficult to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still give them because I want students to run into these human problems in a safer environment, where we can work through them together. Where we can reflect. I hope they become better people as a result. Not by a lot (that would be unrealistic), but by a little. A little less susceptible to tribalism. A little more aware of how to handle abuse when it happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are all just people. Biased without knowing it. Blind to our own faults. Heroes of our own stories who imagine enemies when they don&amp;rsquo;t exist.  Growing up means learning to question ourselves while still trusting ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are we cooked?</title>
      <link>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/are-we-cooked/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/are-we-cooked/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My students frequently ask me what LLMs mean for them as future software developers and data scientists. With little exaggeration it often comes across something along the lines of &amp;ldquo;low-key, are we cooked?&amp;rdquo;. The last one, if you are not one of my students, translates in millennial to &amp;ldquo;good esteemed professor, tell me true, are we f#@ked?&amp;rdquo; While I&amp;rsquo;ve given various off-the-cuff answers, I feel inspired to be more thoughtful in putting down more complete thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;some-personal-background&#34;&gt;Some personal background&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to start by giving a little personal history and just saying I understand the anxiety. I started my freshman year at CalPoly San Luis Obispo in Computer Science in September 1999. Like many of us older millennials that got into tech, I had been programming since elementary school (QBasic!) and computer science seemed a natural path. I always loved reading philosophy though and I seriously considered getting a philosophy degree instead. It was a choice between something I figured I was pretty decent at and could make money doing (computer science) and something that I was personally invested in but probably couldn&amp;rsquo;t make money with (philosophy). Earning a living won out over passion. I stuck with computer science, but I took as many philosophy classes as I could get into. To the extent that I was put on academic probation, not because my grades were too low, but because in the words of the admin &amp;ldquo;stop taking so many philosophy classes and just graduate!&amp;rdquo;. Good times…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within a year of starting my degree, the tech market fell out. March 2000, we saw the dotcom bust, and here I was a computer science student, kind of doing it for the money, kind of not, and my sure bet didn&amp;rsquo;t seem so sure anymore. We also saw a revival of the perennial bugaboo for American software developers: outsourcing. Every decade brought fresh panic that all programming jobs &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.slashdot.org/story/04/10/15/1521231/us-programmers-an-endangered-species?sbsrc=thisday&#34;&gt;would&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://forio.com/about/blog/pitfalls-of-outsourcing-programmers/&#34;&gt;move&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/07/business/business-who-wins-and-who-loses-as-jobs-move-overseas.html&#34;&gt;India&lt;/a&gt;, that American developers were too expensive, that we&amp;rsquo;d all be obsolete. I had to eat and had done a combination of construction and IT jobs up until that point and I was quickly burning through the savings I had built up from working. Luckily, I was able to convince one of my professors, Dr. Clint Staley, to whom I am forever grateful for many reasons, to let me interview for a startup he was running. Working that part-time while I went to school I was able to pay for myself, and momentum carried me forward to finishing my degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;are-we-cooked&#34;&gt;Are we cooked?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best part about teaching in a university is you get to ramble. It is the single most defining characteristic of professors. But I&amp;rsquo;m sure at this point my students are asking: can you get to the point, are we cooked or not? I consider myself a skeptical optimist at heart. Meaning, I&amp;rsquo;m not inclined to believe that change is bad, but I&amp;rsquo;m also more cautious about predicting the future than others. Straightforwardly, that leads me to an answer of no, I don&amp;rsquo;t think you are cooked, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I can tell you with great certainty how things will play out. What I can do is point you towards the toolkit for how to make better decisions here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;embracing-uncertainty&#34;&gt;Embracing uncertainty&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is filled with uncertainty. Many people react irrationally to uncertainty, avoiding it too much or betting too much on luck. Learning how to deal rationally with uncertainty can give you an advantage throughout your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 2010 to 2016, I built and then led the supply chain and capacity planning systems for AWS Infrastructure. My biggest lesson is dollar for dollar, people are overly biased towards investing in prediction when they are often better suited to invest in flexibility. Time series forecasting tools take the past and extend it out to the future. The further out you go, the more variance you get. And black swan style events, like when &lt;a href=&#34;https://spectrum.ieee.org/the-lessons-of-thailands-flood&#34;&gt;Thailand becomes flooded&lt;/a&gt; and you lose a healthy portion of the world&amp;rsquo;s hard-drive manufacturing capacity, are not frequent enough to learn from in a predictable way. Better to get a good enough forecast, but instead focus on shortening your lead-times, making your supply fungible—meaning interchangeable and adaptable to different uses—and late-binding your decisions as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parallel to career planning is direct. You can spend a lot of time trying to accurately predict where LLMs will take the industry and the job market. But that will quickly hit diminishing returns. I would instead approach the question from the other angle: what skills are most likely to be durable and fungible—that is, transferable and valuable across different contexts—in a wide variety of potential outcomes? Going whole hog into &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to build my career around being a React developer&amp;rdquo; is betting on one very specific outcome. If it pays off, great, you can probably command a premium if you turn out to be one of the world&amp;rsquo;s best React developers. But what happens when React joins jQuery in the graveyard of once-essential frameworks?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;an-interlude-about-koalas&#34;&gt;An Interlude about Koalas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I graduated from college, I went to work for Lawrence Livermore National Labs as a computer scientist. I was working on translating large-scale semantic graph algorithms into usable interfaces for intelligence analysts. I had personally received an award from the Secretary of Homeland Security. We had the academic freedom to explore whatever angles we wanted. There was little pressure to meet deadlines. It felt like a safe and secure job for life working in my little niche. My former professor and boss, Dr. Staley, called me up and said his new startup was just acquired by some struggling online bookseller called Amazon. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t super interested, as I could see existing in my current niche for my whole life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He convinced me to join by telling me a story about koalas. Koalas primarily subsist on eucalyptus leaves. Most other animals don&amp;rsquo;t eat eucalyptus, because they have little to no nutrition and they are kind of toxic. But koalas have built their entire evolutionary strategy around being the ones to eat eucalyptus leaves. This has been a great and successful strategy for koalas. But what happens if the eucalyptus forest goes away? Koalas are screwed. Does that mean koalas are actually in danger? No, but it does mean their fate is entirely bound to that one food source existing, while an animal like a rat can happily live and thrive in many ecosystems and is thus much more resistant to shocks in any given ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reason, that story convinced me to give Amazon a chance. Rather than focusing on a more niche area as defining &amp;ldquo;what I did&amp;rdquo; like &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m the person who designs usability for mathematically intensive applications,&amp;rdquo; I instead built my career around solving hard technical problems regardless of the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-are-those-fungible-skills&#34;&gt;What are those fungible skills?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I look back at the skills I learned in university, many of the specific technologies I learned never got used. I learned all about expert systems, but never built an expert system. I learned all about OpenGL, never used it. What I learned from my computer science courses that stuck was the more fundamental ideas of how to think about hard technical problems and create simple, workable solutions to them. For this reason, I often recommend to students who ask me which classes to take that it is more important to take a class that is difficult with a high degree of rigor that challenges you than to focus on any particular domain. Surprisingly, in retrospect, I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten as much use out of the philosophy classes I took—that CalPoly tried to kick me out for taking too many of—as I did my computer science classes. Learning critical thinking skills, how to navigate difficult ethical situations, how to communicate difficult ideas. When Amazon asked me to design a system that could fairly allocate scarce resources across competing teams, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t my coding skills that mattered most—it was my ability to think critically about the problem space and use data to understand and communicate trade-offs to executives who each thought their project was most important. What I&amp;rsquo;d say is my computer science skills were 95% of what initially got me in the door, but it was my liberal arts skills that dominated my later career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my answer is, whatever you do, take on challenging problems, regardless of the area, so you can learn the meta-cognitive skills to understand how you learn and face up to these challenges. Learn critical thinking and how to tear apart problems to turn them from intractable to tractable. And don&amp;rsquo;t neglect the human-side of building your ability to communicate and deal ethically and fairly with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, LLMs are different from outsourcing or the dot-com bust. They can actually write code—not just cheaper, but instantaneously. And yes, I’ve seen the headlines: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2025/03/14/programming-jobs-lost-artificial-intelligence/&#34;&gt;27% of programming jobs are gone&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://wallstreetpit.com/127073-150k-software-engineer-turned-doordasher-after-800-ai-rejections/&#34;&gt;engineers facing hundreds of rejections&lt;/a&gt;. While I’m skeptical that this disruption is solely due to LLMs (e.g., a mix of post COVID overhiring, interest rate hikes, and broader economic shifts) there’s no doubt that a painful market correction is underway. But remember: every technological disruption feels unprecedented while it’s happening. The telephone operators watching automatic switches get installed thought their &lt;a href=&#34;https://thehistoryinsider.com/rise-fall-of-telephone-operators/&#34;&gt;world was ending&lt;/a&gt;. They were right about their specific job—wrong about their ability to adapt. The question isn’t whether LLMs will change things—they will. The question is whether you’ll be a koala or a rat when they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So no, you&amp;rsquo;re not necessarily cooked. But you might be if you specialize too narrowly in whatever framework or language seems hot today. The jobs that are available will be different, and many of the existing software roles will not exist, at least in their current form. Build skills that transfer. Solve hard problems. Learn to think, not just code. The future needs people who can work with AI, not be replaced by it. And that future is built on the same foundation it always was: adaptability, critical thinking, and the uniquely human ability to navigate uncertainty with wisdom rather than fear.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A time to dream</title>
      <link>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/a-time-to-dream/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/a-time-to-dream/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My success in life is based on my love and respect for daydreaming. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been a daydreamer. At the age of seven, I envisioned a space opera of powerful Lizians, Heart Monkeys and Star People who fought against the tyrannical Lizard Men. I loved this world and I visited every chance I got. I spent so much time fleshing out my world rather than school work that by the end of high school I had a written a truly intricate science fiction novel and I had the poor grades to show it. It was also an amazingly horrible novel. When I showed it to a girl I liked in high school, because high school chicks dig sci-fi authors, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t have anticipated the reaction, “I can&amp;rsquo;t believe you waste your time dreaming about stupid stuff like this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To this day, I still waste most of my time “dreaming about stupid stuff.” Most of those dreams now involve my work rather than fantastical worlds, but the love is still there. I set aside several hours every week to dream about what could be. I sprawl out in these dreams, I linger, and I set no goals for myself in what I hope to accomplish. I ask myself, what would make this amazing? Why would that be amazing? What is the essence of amazingness? I go down every corridor, until I get to the essence of the problem and the solution. This isn&amp;rsquo;t work that can measured; this is my time to enjoy myself and untangle life&amp;rsquo;s truly difficult puzzles. It is during these times that I get excited about the potential of what could be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without this time to dream, my work would have no direction. I would be subject to the whims of whomever is yelling the most at a particular moment or whatever crisis of the week has sprung up. Dreaming builds a vision and a vision creates purpose. When something urgent comes up, I can keep it in the context of whether it is truly more important than the great things I&amp;rsquo;ve envisioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where many other dreamers go wrong is their dreams stay dreams. I love my dreams, but I also respect them. That respect means that while I set aside time each week to dream, I spend the rest of my week making them happen. I temper my excitement for the amazingness of what could be by telling myself that greatness takes time. So I take the smallest step possible towards the dream that I can put into action. I then dream again the next week, but this time a smarter me is dreaming, informed by the realities of taking that small step forward. That smarter me comes up with an even better dream. Dream and reality march forward together as the work evolves, always daring to dream of perfection while letting reality take its time to get there. This constant cycle of vision and execution is what leads inevitably to success.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bad Programmer</title>
      <link>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/the-bad-programmer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2008 21:25:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/the-bad-programmer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nick makes a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/in-defense-of-go-to/&#34;&gt;good argument&lt;/a&gt; for why go to should not be used. His closing argument is that zealous programmers will abuse go to. Pete makes a similar argument that go to has too much potential for abuse from programmers that we can&amp;rsquo;t be bothered to explain the use of to and you are better off banning them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a similar argument people make when arguing for gun restrictions. As the politicians will tell you, &amp;ldquo;Sure we trust you with a gun, but do you trust your neighbor or the guys from across town with them?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference though is that you have a lot of choice over who you work with. If you are limiting your choice of language or features based on the fact that you work with bad programmers I think you are trading off against the wrong factor. Do you want to work with bad programmers? Removing dangerous features from a language will certainly remove possibilities from bad programmers shooting themselves in the foot. They still won&amp;rsquo;t be good programmers though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many bad programmers will you even work with? Companies tend to have fairly regular hiring standards, at least at any departmental level and in my experience good programmers tend to work in the same place and bad programmers equally congregate. Indeed, in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Peopleware-Productive-Projects-Teams-Second/dp/0932633439/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;qid=1229231876&amp;amp;sr=1-1&#34;&gt;PeopleWare&lt;/a&gt; they demonstrated a strong correlation between programming ability and the layout of the office where they worked. If there is a strong correlation between office layout and ability then programmers in the same office will have a strong correlation in programming ability amongst themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The boogeyman of bad programmers is a false threat to individual programmers. You are very likely only working with bad programmers if you are a bad programmer yourself. As a good programmer working with other good programmers, is go to still a bad idea?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Persistence: The long lost virtue of fixing a bug</title>
      <link>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/persistence-the-long-lost-virtue-of-fixing-a-bug/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2008 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/persistence-the-long-lost-virtue-of-fixing-a-bug/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heights by great men reached and kept&lt;br&gt;
Were not attained by sudden flight,&lt;br&gt;
But they, while their companions slept,&lt;br&gt;
Were toiling upward in the night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; Henry Wadsworth Longfellow&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re working on a difficult bug. A strange log message showing that your program fails every once in a while. Looking at your watch you see you&amp;rsquo;ve already been working on it for half an hour. You put the bug back on the router thinking to yourself maybe someone else will have better luck. And then a man from the future appears behind you&amp;hellip; oh never mind I won&amp;rsquo;t subject you to that torture &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/do-not-fix-what-you-dont-understand/&#34;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.bonnycode.com/bug2hard.png&#34; alt=&#34;Developer_bug_conversation&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are like most software developers you&amp;rsquo;ve been in the situation above. Maybe instead you mark the bug as &amp;ldquo;Cannot Reproduce&amp;rdquo; or you instead assign it to your resident expert. Regardless of the means you use to escape from fixing the bug, you are dodging an important opportunity. This is normally when I start hearing the excuses. The bug is too hard. Someone else could fix it sooo much faster. There are too many bugs to waste time on just one. Forget the excuses, it is worth it both to you and the product you are creating. Oh let me count the ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are actually learning something deep about the technology you work with. Sure the first time you are learning something you are slow. Really slow. But you are learning. You are dissecting the technology and learning how it really works. In the future with this deep knowledge you will be able to quickly solve problems. You are increasing your skill set as a developer which is good for the company you work for now and for your future marketability later. See Figure 1 below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are wasting the time you spent getting up to speed on the problem. You pick up the bug, spend 30 minutes and then put it back on the router. The next person picks it up, spends 30 minutes and then puts it back on the router. yadda yadda. This is a huge waste of everyone&amp;rsquo;s time. The same if you mark it as cannot reproduce, but instead you are wasting the time of the customer or testers and then more developers later when they bring up the bug again in a new form.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not only is the bug noise on the router, it is also noise in the logs (hopefully you do have some means of tracking errors from your system). It is a common tradition in too many software shops to have their set of ignorable errors that just seem to happen and nobody really knows why but they seem fairly harmless so nobody fixes them. Not to say people didn&amp;rsquo;t try, I&amp;rsquo;m sure at least 5 people spent their 30 minutes on trying to fix it. Noise in the logs is not a good thing though. It could actually be a problem that will only manifest itself at an inopportune time. Even if it is genuinely harmless, it is still one more thing for humans to mentally parse and ignore and distracts away from seeing the real bugs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.bonnycode.com/figure1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure1&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point you maybe be telling yourself &amp;ldquo;Great I&amp;rsquo;m going to fix all the bugs&amp;rdquo;. Look a null pointer exception, all I need is a little if statement null check and I&amp;rsquo;m good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hold On!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resist the urge to cut off the investigation early. Fixing the symptoms of a bug is NOT fixing the bug. Why is that variable null? Is it supposed to be nullable even? You must find the root cause even if it takes you 10 or 20 times longer. Treat the bug as if it was a memory corruption bug. You can try treating each of the various symptoms of the memory corruption and varied they will be. Or you can hit that one spot where it is actually occurring and fix it for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trade off is really this, you can either spend 2 days going deep, really understanding how something works and understanding the core of the issue, or you can spend the next month making tiny one off fixes that treat just the symptoms. In the end sticking with it and finding the real problem is 95% of the time more cost effective than just treating the symptoms. And speaking from experience, it is much more gratifying as well. Figure 2 shows a comparison between fixing the root cause and just fixing the first symptom you can patch over.&lt;br&gt;
[&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.bonnycode.com/figure2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Figure2&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Persistence does not equal stupidity. Banging your head against a problem and making no progress is not persistence anymore than running on a treadmill is a form of transportation. Well&amp;hellip; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.heavy.com/video/61095&#34;&gt;not normally at least&lt;/a&gt;. I see lack of persistence as the biggest thing that holds people back, but many people don&amp;rsquo;t even know how to go about fixing the hard problems. It is a skill and I could go on about divide and conquer, how to actually use google and a million other tidbits. As an honest to goodness skill though, my best advice is to pair up with the best, most knowledgeable bug fixer you know. Who is the developer that ends up actually fixing the really hard problems when they come up? Tackle a really hard problem with them. When you get stuck on a really hard bug, don&amp;rsquo;t give up, but do ask for advice explaining your progress so far. Don&amp;rsquo;t ask them to do the work for you, but do ask for pointers on where to look next. Often times you&amp;rsquo;ll find the act of just explaining what you&amp;rsquo;ve discovered will lead you to the solution on your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember this. Any script kiddie can copy and paste some code, tweak some values and get a system they barely understand to kinda work. If you want to distinguish yourself as a software developer, work to truly understand the system you are building, don&amp;rsquo;t shy away from the difficult problems and don&amp;rsquo;t stop until you really know what is going on.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do not fix what you don&#39;t understand</title>
      <link>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/do-not-fix-what-you-dont-understand/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2008 23:31:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.bonnycode.com/posts/do-not-fix-what-you-dont-understand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s monday at 2pm and you are working on another bug report. It is a null pointer exception in a class you aren&amp;rsquo;t familiar with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kd&#34;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nc&#34;&gt;Nose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kt&#34;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nf&#34;&gt;upYourNoseWithARubberHose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;RubberHose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;hose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;hose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;na&#34;&gt;diameter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;inch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;noseHose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;hose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;      &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;throw&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;HoseTooBigForNoseException&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;....&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;*yawn*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hose is null and a null pointer exception is thrown when accessing its diameter. At least this is an easy fix you think to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;line&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cl&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;hose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;kc&#34;&gt;null&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;||&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;hose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;na&#34;&gt;diameter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;n&#34;&gt;inch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;w&#34;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Awesome&amp;hellip; bug fixed&amp;hellip; just need to commit. &amp;ldquo;Fixed NPE in upYourNoseWithARubberHose&amp;rdquo; you type into the comment box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just before clicking the commit button a whooshing sound comes from behind you. Whirling around you see a huge man with a large gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.bonnycode.com/terminator.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Arnold-schwarzenegger-the-terminator&#34;&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve come from the future and I must stop your bug fix. You have no idea what will happen when you make this change. You didn&amp;rsquo;t reproduce the problem. You didn&amp;rsquo;t find the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Root_cause_analysis&#34;&gt;root cause&lt;/a&gt;. You didn&amp;rsquo;t talk to someone knowledgeable in this part of the code. You didn&amp;rsquo;t find the person who caused the bug and ask them about the fix. You didn&amp;rsquo;t even test your fix. I&amp;rsquo;m sorry but for the sake of the future I can&amp;rsquo;t let you commit that change.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man lowers the gun and fires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your monitor disintegrates into a thousand shards of glass and plastic. Next he shoots your keyboard, the letter q smacks you in the forehead as it flies away from the carnage. Your brand new laser mouse is next. You begin to move your hand to shield it from the oversized rounds this future man is shooting but thinking again you pull it back just before he fires. Finally, he takes aim at your computer. At this point you&amp;rsquo;ve resigned yourself. This man has travelled back in time to stop you from checking in this horribly stupid bug fix and he means to finish the job. He fires and the hard drives spins for its last time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He turns and starts to walk away. Just as he exits the door though he turns and he shoots one of the wheels off your chair. Your chair slumps towards where the now missing wheel was throwing your body to one side. Future man smiles with a satisfaction that only comes from knowing one has done a thorough job. Future man wonders why you couldn&amp;rsquo;t have been as thorough in your own bug fixing in finding the root cause of the problem before carelessly throwing around fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you sit in the carnage of your computer equipment, slanted to one side in your broken chair, smelling the still fresh smoke you think over what you learned today. The future man&amp;rsquo;s words echo in your brain&amp;hellip;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ldquo;You have no idea what will happen when you make this change. You didn&amp;rsquo;t reproduce the problem. You didn&amp;rsquo;t find the root cause. You didn&amp;rsquo;t talk to someone knowledgeable in this part of the code. You didn&amp;rsquo;t find the person who caused the bug and ask them about the fix. You didn&amp;rsquo;t even test your fix.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your left to ponder what future your simple bug fix had unintentionally caused that it would induce man to invent time travel to send someone back to stop you. Truly horrible it must have been and with that you promise in the name of the future man with the big gun to never make another bug fix on a problem that you don&amp;rsquo;t understand.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
