<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Meritocracy on BonnyCode</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/meritocracy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Meritocracy on BonnyCode</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/meritocracy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Directions to New York</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/directions-to-new-york/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/directions-to-new-york/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Long, long ago, I was born at home in Southeast LA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a kid I didn&amp;rsquo;t know where I wanted to go. People said, &amp;ldquo;follow your heart.&amp;rdquo; Mine whispered: &amp;ldquo;find good food.&amp;rdquo; But where was that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An old teacher told an epic tale of his own journey. He credited Epicurus as a guide. I&amp;rsquo;ve never read that magazine but I think it has to do with fancy food. I saw genuine joy as he recounted his travels. It&amp;rsquo;s too bad I wanted directions, not grand stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided I wanted to move to Bremerton. An uncle had been stationed there years ago, and in my imagination it was a land of good coffee and better sushi. The lack of sun that drove others away seemed, to me, like comfort. I asked my parents for the way but they didn&amp;rsquo;t know. California was already their dream compared to Missoura. They couldn&amp;rsquo;t understand my desire to eat better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I started walking. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t exactly sure where Bremerton was, but I knew it was somewhere up north. I found other people on the road. I would stop to chat, but they were too slow and I hurried past. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been a fast walker who didn&amp;rsquo;t tire easily. After three days of continuous walking, I got shin splints. I slowed and others passed me. A stranger, soon a friend, helped me make those last miles to Bakersfield. Two weeks gone, and the road ahead already looked endless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I settled into Bakersfield, resting at a honky-tonk and steeling myself for the next leg north. Mostly I stayed at the bar, drinking, listening to a poorly received Ray Price cover band, and to the dreams of strangers. One old oil man recalled his youth in New York City. To him it was the center of the universe, where well-dressed people dined at the best restaurants and controlled the world. His nostalgia became my dream. But how was I to find the way?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I started asking people already in New York. &amp;ldquo;Hey youse, how&amp;rsquo;d you get there?&amp;rdquo; One guy said he was born in New York; lucky bastard. Why did I have to cross the country when he simply arrived at birth? A woman told me she&amp;rsquo;d taken the train from Boston. If only I could do the same; board in the morning, arrive in Manhattan by lunch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s funny to look back at trips that once felt impossible and now seem trivial. I sometimes wonder, naively: why didn&amp;rsquo;t I just take a plane? At the time I&amp;rsquo;d never flown, and couldn&amp;rsquo;t have afforded it anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I finally left the honky-tonk, I met a man with a bicycle. He said the bicycle was the way to go and generously offered to lend it. My lucky break. I climbed on and started pedaling. I never returned the bike, and for a long time I carried guilt about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I biked as far as Barstow, ready to take the 40 east toward Phoenix on my way to New York. But it was midsummer, and another kind soul stopped me. &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;ll kill yourself riding through the desert in this heat,&amp;rdquo; she said, and offered me a ride in her van. I climbed in, and we drove all the way to Las Vegas. It was just her destination, though to me it felt closer to Phoenix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a bus stop outside the library, I saw an advertisement: the Eiffel Tower, a rhino, and a man declaring &amp;ldquo;J&amp;rsquo;aime la France.&amp;rdquo; It looked impossibly exotic. Paris was surely better than New York. Didn&amp;rsquo;t Paris have more Michelin restaurants than anywhere else? (It doesn&amp;rsquo;t, but I get these things wrong all the time.) Ignorance was bliss, and I was in a dream; a dream impossible to reach by bike or by foot. So I found a map, made a new plan, and took a job in Las Vegas to save for a used Toyota Corolla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lived in Las Vegas for two years. It isn&amp;rsquo;t what tourists imagine. The city has two faces. The one I knew had Station Casinos, rodeos, LDS wards, and panaderías somehow thriving together. A dust bowl of down-to-earth folk who never set foot on the Strip yet were tied to it all the same. A place where people came to get rich quick and ended up poor. I&amp;rsquo;m glad I left, but I miss the people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;d saved enough, I bought a car and drove to Corpus Christi. An old friend there taught me how to sail. Paris was waiting, and I was going to cross the ocean to get there. I practiced every day until I grew confident. Nothing could stop me now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sold the Corolla and bought an old sailboat, which I fixed up as best I could. Leaving my friend was hard, but Paris was waiting, and I set off. I hugged the coast of the Gulf of—well, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to get political—but I stayed close to shore until Florida. When I finally struck out across the ocean, a storm hit. I barely limped my broken boat to shore near Nassau. I&amp;rsquo;m lucky to be alive; I still wonder by what grace I survived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nassau was paradise. The weather was kind, the people generous, the food simple and extraordinary. I made a life there. It feels like another world now, separate from the one before and the one after. And I was another person: freer, and for the first time without obligations to anyone but myself. Then I thought I had discovered a more authentic life; now I think it was simply a different one. I could go on and on, but it was only a diversion. Eventually I fixed the boat and moved on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sailed up the coast and stopped in Charleston, intending it to be quick. I&amp;rsquo;d eaten shrimp and grits separately before, but Charleston perfected them together. One of my old walking companions from California had settled there, and she was ill. I stayed to care for her. I was already behind on my journey, and now I was falling further back. Others who had once trailed me were surely ahead by now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we had the best of times. We told terrible, meandering jokes with punchlines like, &amp;ldquo;you don&amp;rsquo;t eat a pig that good all at once.&amp;rdquo; Jokes hilarious to the teller, greeted mostly with groans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oftentimes tragedy clarifies what really matters and clears the way to a truer life. Other times, grief makes you stupid. A friend with a plane stopped in Charleston on his way to Philadelphia and asked if I needed a ride. We flew together. I didn&amp;rsquo;t like it there. The bread was overrated, the whiz unnecessary, the winters too cold. It simply wasn&amp;rsquo;t my place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned there was a train from Philadelphia to New York City and boarded it with excitement. This was what I had once dreamed of. But New York wasn&amp;rsquo;t what I imagined. People spoke of the pizza as if it were life-changing; it was just okay. The coffee was no better than back home. Maybe I had hyped it up too much. Or maybe something was wrong with me, since everyone else seemed to love it. I tried to fix myself. I read Rhonda Byrne: too woo. I read Robert Greene: too evil. I read Paulo Coelho: too on the nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, despite my discomfort, I was now known as &amp;ldquo;the New Yorker.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it was because I had a family of my own. My kids were difficult. They complained about the constant moving. I tried to slow down for them, but the world told me to hurry up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Are you still in New York?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ldquo;Wow, look at the townie.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I kept moving. I told myself I could spend time with my kids when I got there, wherever &amp;ldquo;there&amp;rdquo; was. But eventually I broke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went back to my little corner of not-quite Los Angeles. But home wasn&amp;rsquo;t home anymore. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t tell if I had changed, or if home had. Probably both. The home I carried in my head, a place of rest and retreat, was nowhere to be found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then one morning I woke on a flight to Seoul. Ah, this was it. In New York, everyone dreamed of Seoul; at least that&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;d learned there. Online I saw the cities ranked by tier: Philadelphia, then New York, then Seoul, then Tokyo. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t believe I once thought New York was the peak. What a fool I was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was immediately known as &amp;ldquo;the Seoul Brother.&amp;rdquo; It felt wrong, on the verge of offensive, but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t control what people called me. One Halloween I tried bibimbap in the Asiana lounge at ICN. It was good, though I expected it to be spicier. Right after, the airport staged a mini cultural parade, staff dressed in traditional Korean costumes. I wondered what my kids dressed as that year. I didn&amp;rsquo;t have time to find out; I had an early flight to Tokyo. Thank the Lord, my elite status cleared an upgrade to business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I quickly became known as &amp;ldquo;Tokyo Man.&amp;rdquo; The titles had grown consistently gendered, and when I pointed it out, the dirty looks reminded me how hard it was to learn which critiques were acceptable and which were not. Still, I was adapting. How parochial I had once been, thinking Seattle (or worse, Bremerton) was the place for good sushi. By now I was good at blending in, mimicking the language and the values:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Gesha kōhī o hitotsu onegaishimasu.&lt;/em&gt; (One coffee, please.)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ōma no ōtoro o ikkan onegaishimasu.&lt;/em&gt; (One sushi, please.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I missed biscuits and gravy. I found a pop-up serving them in HND Terminal 3 and was thrilled. My dad used to make them every holiday: Bisquick biscuits, cheap sausage browned in a pan, then flour, milk, salt, and pepper whisked into the drippings. One Mother&amp;rsquo;s Day, we ran out of mix and we tried to stretch it with some flour. &amp;ldquo;Someone&amp;rdquo; grabbed the wrong canister and added powdered sugar instead of flour. They came out glazed and blackened, but we ate them anyway, laughing at ourselves for mistaking sugar for flour. The airport version wasn&amp;rsquo;t funny, just wrong; the gravy was plasticky, the biscuits both greasy and dry. I missed my kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company put me on their jet to Shenzhen. It was hard to believe I ever endured the chaos of commercial travel with the masses. I was told everything would be better in Shenzhen. That I would have finally arrived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I built a boat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked my family where they wanted to go, and we sailed. We were silly. We told stories. There were more tears, and more laughter. More death, but also more life. It felt right in a way I can&amp;rsquo;t quite explain. Along the way we met others and stopped to play spades and dominoes; and complicated board games we were lucky to play twice. Maybe learning the rules was half the fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A stranger was amazed I had once been &lt;em&gt;Tokyo Man.&lt;/em&gt; It felt like a lie even when it was true. He said I was ungrateful for turning away from such privilege. Maybe I am. But I wasn&amp;rsquo;t born on a sailboat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So our family sailed to San Luis Obispo. The coffee isn&amp;rsquo;t the best in the world, but it&amp;rsquo;s darn good. We like it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My best life choices could be printed on kitschy signs from HomeGoods. I wonder how many truths I&amp;rsquo;ve dodged simply because they felt too trite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A kid from Seattle asks me, &amp;ldquo;How do I get to New York?&amp;rdquo; Another asks, &amp;ldquo;Why New York, and not London or Paris?&amp;rdquo; Yet another: &amp;ldquo;Was it skill that got you there, speed, or just luck?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
