<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Computer-Science on BonnyCode</title>
    <link>http://localhost:49476/tags/computer-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Computer-Science on BonnyCode</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:49476/tags/computer-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Work Hard, Have Fun, Go Home</title>
      <link>http://localhost:49476/posts/work-hard-have-fun-go-home/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:49476/posts/work-hard-have-fun-go-home/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;hus·tle cul·ture&lt;/strong&gt;  ˈhə-səl ˈkəl-chər&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;noun&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the performance of results when actual results are missing; specif.: a workplace ethos where the appearance of extreme effort is rewarded more than the achievement of tangible outcomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a management technique characterized by demanding longer work hours to compensate for a lack of strategic direction or a lack of management domain knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;archaic&lt;/em&gt;: the belief that professional success is directly and exclusively proportional to the time spent engaged in work-related activities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See also&lt;/em&gt;: performative work, burnout culture, toxic productivity&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could lecture you on the dangers of burnout in tech, the importance of having a life outside your job, and the ethics of exploitation. For many ambitious, high-achieving young engineers and students, those warnings simply don’t matter. The thinking is: I’m at a point in life when I can work hard and put in long hours, so why not? I’ll reap the benefits later. I’ll go where hard work is most rewarded and live for the hustle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was the same early in my working life. I tried to log as many hours as I could. My first jobs were paid hourly, so more hours meant more pay. I loved it when overtime was approved; it meant my bills were paid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I moved into a salaried tech role, I kept working long hours even without the direct financial incentive. Part of it was insecurity: I worried I wasn’t as smart as people thought, so I worked extra to meet expectations. I hid how much I was working so people would think I was effortlessly talented. I went home when everyone else did, then devoured books, built simulations, and pursued deep understanding. Older mentors talked about paying your dues and building a strong work ethic for life. And the truth is, I often just loved the work. Solving difficult problems was fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;just-power-through&#34;&gt;Just power through&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a tech lead in an organization run by a GM who lived and breathed rise and grind. His credentials were impeccable (think, Harvard MBA, McKinsey, straight to GM). And he was furious when things didn’t go his way. I mostly avoided his wrath because my team hit our goals. But the teams that missed a deadline? Mandatory weekends in the office, late nights, daily standups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made the mistake of dialing into a large project meeting right before a long-planned family trip. One of my sister teams announced that a project due the next week was suddenly red and likely to slip by weeks. My GM exploded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I became excited for my time to speak. My projects were going well, I thought their disaster would make me look better in comparison. And I was on that pre-vacation high, thinking about margaritas and the time I needed with family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I said in a tone that was unmistakably smug:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“All our projects are on track and running as expected. As a reminder, I’ll be out next week in Cabo and won’t make next week’s meeting.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silence. I’d miscalculated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;strong&gt;NO!&lt;/strong&gt; NO VACATIONS! This is a code red! You are going to help the project get on track! We are all one team here!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I protested that I knew nothing about the project. I even tried to cite &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peopleware:_Productive_Projects_and_Teams&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Peopleware&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. All the wrong things to say. I was ordered to cancel my time off, join the team over the weekend, and personally guarantee the launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I canceled my trip; the rest of my family went, just without me. I tried to help the project but had no context. I was also tired; my body and mind had already prepared for a break and now it was yanked away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project was eventually abandoned before it ever launched. Several months later the GM stopped showing up to any meetings. A week-and-a-half later we got an email from our VP: our GM had taken a new role and they were looking for a replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-little-right-beats-a-lot-of-wrong&#34;&gt;A little right beats a lot of wrong&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was a turning point for me. Something broke in me: I stopped seeing the world as a list of tasks that just needed dev hours applied to them. Rather than work that weekend (my typical routine), I went to a coffee shop and just relaxed. My mind naturally went to reflection and I pulled out my notebook. I started planning. I could either be a victim of the unfairness in the world or I could strategize. I chose the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That became my go-to strategy for the rest of my career, and it served me far better than my “just power through it” approach ever did. The beauty of tech, unlike when I was a laborer on construction sites, is that there is often a ten-times better way to solve a problem in tech. What you actually need to build is usually less clear than people realize, and once you do understand it, there are often much simpler ways to get there. Overbuilding is the default in tech, usually because they never took the time to clarify the real need. The result is a generic monstrosity that only half solves the problem. Once you recognize that, you start to see opportunities to approach problems differently. But you cannot do that if you are stuck in stressed, execution-only mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;symptoms-of-hustle-culture&#34;&gt;Symptoms of hustle culture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most dangerous thing about hustle culture isn’t just the long hours; it’s the systems it creates. Burnout becomes normal, vacations disappear, and leaders learn to paper over failure with stories of sacrifice. You see the same patterns everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;vacations-that-never-happen&#34;&gt;Vacations that never happen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first joined AWS, I shadowed all the roles in the overall process I was going to automate; a process involving billions of dollars in infrastructure purchases. I was terrified when I discovered a single mid-level employee owned one of the steps in the critical path. They were the only person who had ever done the step. No one else knew how to do it. They scheduled their time off around performing that one step, and hadn’t taken a vacation longer than a week as a result since taking on the role. A single point-of-failure, dutifully keeping an empire running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a company culture demands always being on, it invites these types of systematic risks. Smaller versions exist on every team: the “indispensable” developer who never fully disconnects. Until they leave and you discover the trail of things they owned starting to fall apart. One of my first audits as a manager is simple: check when people last took real leave. Not a day off, but at least one week, preferably three. If it’s been over a year, that’s a red flag. It’s the easiest way to spot single points-of-failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-you-want-at-3-am&#34;&gt;Who you want at 3 a.m.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of my teams required on-call duties. The engineers I trusted in those rotations weren’t the ones who glorified all-nighters. They were the ones who slept, took breaks, and stayed calm. At 3 a.m., clarity matters more than brute force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people I don’t want on call are the &lt;em&gt;heroes&lt;/em&gt; who think every problem can be solved by powering through. I’ve inherited teams with one developer who lived perpetually on call. That’s not dedication; it’s a disaster waiting to happen. It means no one else understands those systems, no one else can step in to help. And what happens if two of their systems break at the same time? Who are you going to bring in then?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;effort-as-a-cover-story&#34;&gt;Effort as a cover story&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe a meaningful amount of the promotion of hustle culture is actually just covering for failure. I’ve helped companies with the metrics-side of public statements for many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When results are good, leaders talk about results. When results are bad, leaders talk about some obscure metric trending upward. When everything is bad, leaders talk about how hard everyone is working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s what I assume when founders post something like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baby born two hours ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No time for sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m back at the keyboard grinding on my lifelong dream: catpu.ai — Agentic AI for Cat Litterboxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what it takes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;#founderlife #backtowork&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or when a CEO says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We work long, hard, and smart; two out of three doesn’t cut it. Our competition is working seven days a week, 15 hours a day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the product were compelling, they’d talk about the product. If the company was doing what it needed to, they’d talk about that. If they had a strategy to lead the company forward and innovate, they’d preach it from the rooftops. But when they don’t, the message becomes &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=r8miwsWtzRw&#34;&gt;“can you guys, um, work harder?”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered different reasons otherwise smart people fall into this pattern of thinking. I’ve met the consultant-turned-executive who, after being trained on maximizing billable-hours, still thinks hours equal revenue. I’ve seen the non-technical leader who doesn’t understand what the team does, but just assumes the more, of whatever &lt;em&gt;it&lt;/em&gt; is, the better. I’ve observed the too-far-away leader who is overwhelmed with the size of their org and is left with email blasts such as: &amp;ldquo;plz guys, can you just push until the goals are green?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-death-spiral&#34;&gt;The Death Spiral&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Push these symptoms far enough and you hit the Death Spiral. It always starts the same way: a missed goal, a new threat, leadership with no clear plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say we’re working at a social media company when TikTok first came out. At first, the company says: “not a big deal, totally different business than us”. Video view time starts decreasing. Maybe we broke something? Tell the engineers to look for any bugs. Meanwhile, once-golden demographics like US 15-22 year olds stopped showing up. What can be wrong? Then things get much worse. View time starts to nosedive. The engineers say nothing is broken, customers just aren’t showing up. Marketing reports are coming back saying our users are on TikTok. Competitive analysis points in the same direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you do? Now this is an emergency. You start the daily executive meeting to re-establish a sense of control. The CEO joins, your head of engineering, your head of product, some key engineers and product managers. Then the meeting grows and becomes more frantic. More action items are given. And they need to be done tomorrow. Tensions are high. No one wants to say the wrong thing. No one wants to push back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the people on the ground, it’s no longer: &lt;em&gt;‘How do I build a product people will love?’&lt;/em&gt; Instead it becomes: &lt;em&gt;‘Please Lord, get me through this meeting without getting fired.’&lt;/em&gt; Survival replaces results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team works more but accomplishes less. The best engineers leave, because they can. Progress collapses. Deadlines slip. Executives tighten their grip until—congratulations—they’ve killed the puppy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fear. Anxiety. Stress. These are not the ingredients for success. If that’s your leadership’s plan in a crisis, run. Innovation beats exhaustion every time. And exhausted teams rarely innovate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;building-runways-doesnt-bring-planes&#34;&gt;Building runways doesn&amp;rsquo;t bring planes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long hours arise for different reasons. When young engineers work late because they’re genuinely obsessed with a problem, good managers teach discipline to sustain that enthusiasm. When teams work late because management demands it, you get theater: a simulacrum of enthusiasm without the corresponding breakthroughs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weak leaders see correlation (successful teams sometimes work long hours) and force the causation backwards, as if excellence spontaneously arises from butts-in-seat. They set goals on the easy thing, hours, because they can’t create the hard thing: genuine engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best managers spend more time pulling excited engineers away from keyboards than pushing tired ones toward them. They protect the flame of creativity from burning out rather than trying to extract it through force. The worst? They celebrate their suffering hoping people assume it was worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-my-ambitious-students&#34;&gt;To my ambitious students&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re ambitious, don’t join the team making a virtue of late nights. Join the one building things they’re genuinely excited about and still going home for dinner. The best work happens when people have the energy and clarity to innovate, not when they’re competing to prove who can grind the hardest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work hard and have fun. But more importantly, take care of yourself. When you sacrifice everything for your job, you risk becoming someone whose only identity is a title; the person who, years later, still introduces themselves not by who they are, but by what they used to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That loss of self is the same trap hustle culture sets for your career. The person who believes late nights are the only answer eventually stops learning new answers. As a manager, I never promoted someone already at the edge; they simply had no capacity left to grow. Advancement comes from finding better ways to get more done, not by spending more hours in the same old ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you truly want to aim high, remember this: The best teams aren&amp;rsquo;t defined by the hours they put in, but by the value they put out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are we cooked?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:49476/posts/are-we-cooked/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:49476/posts/are-we-cooked/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My students frequently ask me what LLMs mean for them as future software developers and data scientists. With little exaggeration it often comes across something along the lines of &amp;ldquo;low-key, are we cooked?&amp;rdquo;. The last one, if you are not one of my students, translates in millennial to &amp;ldquo;good esteemed professor, tell me true, are we f#@ked?&amp;rdquo; While I&amp;rsquo;ve given various off-the-cuff answers, I feel inspired to be more thoughtful in putting down more complete thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;some-personal-background&#34;&gt;Some personal background&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to start by giving a little personal history and just saying I understand the anxiety. I started my freshman year at CalPoly San Luis Obispo in Computer Science in September 1999. Like many of us older millennials that got into tech, I had been programming since elementary school (QBasic!) and computer science seemed a natural path. I always loved reading philosophy though and I seriously considered getting a philosophy degree instead. It was a choice between something I figured I was pretty decent at and could make money doing (computer science) and something that I was personally invested in but probably couldn&amp;rsquo;t make money with (philosophy). Earning a living won out over passion. I stuck with computer science, but I took as many philosophy classes as I could get into. To the extent that I was put on academic probation, not because my grades were too low, but because in the words of the admin &amp;ldquo;stop taking so many philosophy classes and just graduate!&amp;rdquo;. Good times…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within a year of starting my degree, the tech market fell out. March 2000, we saw the dotcom bust, and here I was a computer science student, kind of doing it for the money, kind of not, and my sure bet didn&amp;rsquo;t seem so sure anymore. We also saw a revival of the perennial bugaboo for American software developers: outsourcing. Every decade brought fresh panic that all programming jobs &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.slashdot.org/story/04/10/15/1521231/us-programmers-an-endangered-species?sbsrc=thisday&#34;&gt;would&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://forio.com/about/blog/pitfalls-of-outsourcing-programmers/&#34;&gt;move&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/07/business/business-who-wins-and-who-loses-as-jobs-move-overseas.html&#34;&gt;India&lt;/a&gt;, that American developers were too expensive, that we&amp;rsquo;d all be obsolete. I had to eat and had done a combination of construction and IT jobs up until that point and I was quickly burning through the savings I had built up from working. Luckily, I was able to convince one of my professors, Dr. Clint Staley, to whom I am forever grateful for many reasons, to let me interview for a startup he was running. Working that part-time while I went to school I was able to pay for myself, and momentum carried me forward to finishing my degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;are-we-cooked&#34;&gt;Are we cooked?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best part about teaching in a university is you get to ramble. It is the single most defining characteristic of professors. But I&amp;rsquo;m sure at this point my students are asking: can you get to the point, are we cooked or not? I consider myself a skeptical optimist at heart. Meaning, I&amp;rsquo;m not inclined to believe that change is bad, but I&amp;rsquo;m also more cautious about predicting the future than others. Straightforwardly, that leads me to an answer of no, I don&amp;rsquo;t think you are cooked, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I can tell you with great certainty how things will play out. What I can do is point you towards the toolkit for how to make better decisions here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;embracing-uncertainty&#34;&gt;Embracing uncertainty&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is filled with uncertainty. Many people react irrationally to uncertainty, avoiding it too much or betting too much on luck. Learning how to deal rationally with uncertainty can give you an advantage throughout your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 2010 to 2016, I built and then led the supply chain and capacity planning systems for AWS Infrastructure. My biggest lesson is dollar for dollar, people are overly biased towards investing in prediction when they are often better suited to invest in flexibility. Time series forecasting tools take the past and extend it out to the future. The further out you go, the more variance you get. And black swan style events, like when &lt;a href=&#34;https://spectrum.ieee.org/the-lessons-of-thailands-flood&#34;&gt;Thailand becomes flooded&lt;/a&gt; and you lose a healthy portion of the world&amp;rsquo;s hard-drive manufacturing capacity, are not frequent enough to learn from in a predictable way. Better to get a good enough forecast, but instead focus on shortening your lead-times, making your supply fungible—meaning interchangeable and adaptable to different uses—and late-binding your decisions as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parallel to career planning is direct. You can spend a lot of time trying to accurately predict where LLMs will take the industry and the job market. But that will quickly hit diminishing returns. I would instead approach the question from the other angle: what skills are most likely to be durable and fungible—that is, transferable and valuable across different contexts—in a wide variety of potential outcomes? Going whole hog into &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to build my career around being a React developer&amp;rdquo; is betting on one very specific outcome. If it pays off, great, you can probably command a premium if you turn out to be one of the world&amp;rsquo;s best React developers. But what happens when React joins jQuery in the graveyard of once-essential frameworks?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;an-interlude-about-koalas&#34;&gt;An Interlude about Koalas&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I graduated from college, I went to work for Lawrence Livermore National Labs as a computer scientist. I was working on translating large-scale semantic graph algorithms into usable interfaces for intelligence analysts. I had personally received an award from the Secretary of Homeland Security. We had the academic freedom to explore whatever angles we wanted. There was little pressure to meet deadlines. It felt like a safe and secure job for life working in my little niche. My former professor and boss, Dr. Staley, called me up and said his new startup was just acquired by some struggling online bookseller called Amazon. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t super interested, as I could see existing in my current niche for my whole life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He convinced me to join by telling me a story about koalas. Koalas primarily subsist on eucalyptus leaves. Most other animals don&amp;rsquo;t eat eucalyptus, because they have little to no nutrition and they are kind of toxic. But koalas have built their entire evolutionary strategy around being the ones to eat eucalyptus leaves. This has been a great and successful strategy for koalas. But what happens if the eucalyptus forest goes away? Koalas are screwed. Does that mean koalas are actually in danger? No, but it does mean their fate is entirely bound to that one food source existing, while an animal like a rat can happily live and thrive in many ecosystems and is thus much more resistant to shocks in any given ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reason, that story convinced me to give Amazon a chance. Rather than focusing on a more niche area as defining &amp;ldquo;what I did&amp;rdquo; like &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m the person who designs usability for mathematically intensive applications,&amp;rdquo; I instead built my career around solving hard technical problems regardless of the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-are-those-fungible-skills&#34;&gt;What are those fungible skills?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I look back at the skills I learned in university, many of the specific technologies I learned never got used. I learned all about expert systems, but never built an expert system. I learned all about OpenGL, never used it. What I learned from my computer science courses that stuck was the more fundamental ideas of how to think about hard technical problems and create simple, workable solutions to them. For this reason, I often recommend to students who ask me which classes to take that it is more important to take a class that is difficult with a high degree of rigor that challenges you than to focus on any particular domain. Surprisingly, in retrospect, I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten as much use out of the philosophy classes I took—that CalPoly tried to kick me out for taking too many of—as I did my computer science classes. Learning critical thinking skills, how to navigate difficult ethical situations, how to communicate difficult ideas. When Amazon asked me to design a system that could fairly allocate scarce resources across competing teams, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t my coding skills that mattered most—it was my ability to think critically about the problem space and use data to understand and communicate trade-offs to executives who each thought their project was most important. What I&amp;rsquo;d say is my computer science skills were 95% of what initially got me in the door, but it was my liberal arts skills that dominated my later career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my answer is, whatever you do, take on challenging problems, regardless of the area, so you can learn the meta-cognitive skills to understand how you learn and face up to these challenges. Learn critical thinking and how to tear apart problems to turn them from intractable to tractable. And don&amp;rsquo;t neglect the human-side of building your ability to communicate and deal ethically and fairly with others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, LLMs are different from outsourcing or the dot-com bust. They can actually write code—not just cheaper, but instantaneously. And yes, I’ve seen the headlines: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2025/03/14/programming-jobs-lost-artificial-intelligence/&#34;&gt;27% of programming jobs are gone&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://wallstreetpit.com/127073-150k-software-engineer-turned-doordasher-after-800-ai-rejections/&#34;&gt;engineers facing hundreds of rejections&lt;/a&gt;. While I’m skeptical that this disruption is solely due to LLMs (e.g., a mix of post COVID overhiring, interest rate hikes, and broader economic shifts) there’s no doubt that a painful market correction is underway. But remember: every technological disruption feels unprecedented while it’s happening. The telephone operators watching automatic switches get installed thought their &lt;a href=&#34;https://thehistoryinsider.com/rise-fall-of-telephone-operators/&#34;&gt;world was ending&lt;/a&gt;. They were right about their specific job—wrong about their ability to adapt. The question isn’t whether LLMs will change things—they will. The question is whether you’ll be a koala or a rat when they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So no, you&amp;rsquo;re not necessarily cooked. But you might be if you specialize too narrowly in whatever framework or language seems hot today. The jobs that are available will be different, and many of the existing software roles will not exist, at least in their current form. Build skills that transfer. Solve hard problems. Learn to think, not just code. The future needs people who can work with AI, not be replaced by it. And that future is built on the same foundation it always was: adaptability, critical thinking, and the uniquely human ability to navigate uncertainty with wisdom rather than fear.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
