<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Abuse on BonnyCode</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/abuse/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Abuse on BonnyCode</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/abuse/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Epistemology of Being an Asshole</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/epistemology-of-being-an-asshole/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/epistemology-of-being-an-asshole/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the early 2000s, I worked for a digital video processing startup that was acquired by Autodesk. Our startup was merged with another acquisition, with our startup largely making up the software developers and the other startup (the &amp;ldquo;others&amp;rdquo;) largely becoming the management layer. The others were clueless: they didn&amp;rsquo;t understand the technical domain, they didn&amp;rsquo;t understand our customers, and didn&amp;rsquo;t understand the product. Naturally, I hated the others. They&amp;rsquo;d schedule meetings that were always a waste of time; I learned to avoid them. Their product plan was a disaster and could never work. We secretly made our own plan and worked on our own better version of the product. Once upper management saw how much better our version of the product was we&amp;rsquo;d be able to finally get rid of the others and everything would be good again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One morning, we were all called into a conference room. At first I tried to skip since I figured it was yet another meeting instigated by the others, but I was told by HR it was mandatory. Everyone was there. We were all laid off, effective immediately. Our whole department was shut down; us, the others, everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the hate, politics, everything just evaporated. We were all just people sitting in a room together. I felt silly and embarrassed for how I felt just moments before. I still do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;slurs-and-more-slurs&#34;&gt;Slurs and more slurs&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first joined Amazon, I was with a recently acquired disc-on-demand startup based out of San Luis Obispo (known affectionately as SLO). This was part of Amazon&amp;rsquo;s strategy to increase content selection by producing physical goods on-demand, allowing Amazon to list long-tail (meaning not very popular) content and we&amp;rsquo;d make it when someone ordered it in the fulfillment center. At the same time, they acquired a book-on-demand startup. Amazon&amp;rsquo;s plan for the two startups was to turn them into an overall content-on-demand service called CreateSpace. I led the low-level video ingestion efforts which had no overlap with the book-on-demand startup. It was a great team and one of the best times I ever had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was told once that Amazon is like a cake-eating contest where the reward for eating the most cake was more cake. Well, my reward in this case was owning a broader scope that included interacting with the folks from the book-on-demand team for the first time. I had heard rumors that the integration was not entirely smooth. I was older and wiser at this point though, I understood tribalism, and I had grown past such petty concerns. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t worried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was excited when I made my first trip to the book-on-demand office to meet the team and get to know them. I learned so much on the trip. Like did you know the reason they call us the SLO office? It is because &amp;ldquo;y&amp;rsquo;all are retarded&amp;rdquo; (get it we are SLOw).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon loved abbreviations (frugality is a core value), and they saved eight letters by abbreviating CreateSpace to CSP. On my trip, I learned CSP didn&amp;rsquo;t actually stand for CreateSpace though, it actually stands for &amp;ldquo;cock-sucking pussies&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So things were worse than I realized. And to be fair, this was a small, small minority, most people were absolutely wonderful and hospitable. But some people were very, very bitter about the two teams merging and they thought it meant they were losing out. When I brought up the &amp;ldquo;politics being not so good between the teams&amp;rdquo; to senior leadership, I was told there is no politics, everybody is on board and being a team player. I made note that leaders don&amp;rsquo;t like when politics is pointed out in their teams; better to pretend it doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;im-going-to-kick-your-ass&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to kick your ass&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much later at Amazon, I was leading a large software development team in AWS. Two software developer interns from another organization in AWS came to talk to me in my office on a Friday morning. I had never met them before and I don&amp;rsquo;t know how they found me or why they came to me. They had been assigned to a non-software organization and they were in the final weeks of their internship. They had never committed any code. They were worried that they hadn&amp;rsquo;t done any real software work and that it would prevent them from getting a return offer. I asked why they waited until now to say anything and they told me it was because they were scared of their management and felt isolated. I looped in campus recruiting to tell them the situation, asked how interns got assigned to a non-software team, how they got through almost their entire internship without a check-in from anybody, and asked what can be done to salvage the situation as best as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later that night, I was getting a beer with a friend. I got a call from an unknown number and let it go to voicemail. Listening to the voicemail at the end of the night, it was from the VP of the organization with the interns: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to kick your fuckin ass the next time I see you. You need to watch yourself, you messed with the wrong fuckin guy.&amp;rdquo; I had met this VP before in large meetings, but never worked with him. He must have looked up my number in the phone tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I told leadership, I found out what a good guy he actually is. He is just very passionate about protecting his team. And, more importantly, he is irreplaceable. Nobody can do what he does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve still never actually talked to him. He never brought it up to me again and didn&amp;rsquo;t actually jump me as promised. I really should have put in a peer review that he lacked follow through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-best-developer-i-ever-worked-with&#34;&gt;The best developer I ever worked with&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I once managed a developer, we will call him Jake. In my eyes, he was the 10x developer made manifest. Jake&amp;rsquo;s speed was only a portion of his value though. What really set him apart is I could throw him at ambiguous problems that stumped other developers. His solutions were not always the most elegant, but he was a solver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was first interviewing Jake, one of my existing team members, we&amp;rsquo;ll call him Rick, warned me that they had worked with Jake before and he had a bad reputation. Jake was a fantastic developer, but he did not play well with others. Rick told me about a situation where Jake called another developer&amp;rsquo;s solution idiotic. I asked if Jake was right, was the solution good. Rick admitted that the solution was not good and that Jake had a better technical strategy. I hired Jake. I loved to work with the best developers. I could manage difficult personalities. I thought then that is what set me apart as a manager, being able to wrangle the best of the best successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, Jake continued to outperform. He also continued to cause me increasing amounts of trouble. I had to regularly move him to work with different teams because people couldn&amp;rsquo;t stand to work with him. People would complain about Jake and I would explain he is actually a nice guy. Jake was always on good behavior around me. I would explain to people he is just passionate about what he does. I would try to smooth things over. I thought Jake was irreplaceable. I thought the productivity was worth it; his behavior towards others was abstract for me while his performance was concrete and helped me hit S-team goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was now the manager who let the jerk into the building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-hero-that-faltered&#34;&gt;The hero that faltered&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was later at Snap, I had grown past all this immaturity. I was fully self-actualized. Leading the data team was tough, because it often felt like we were bullied. My team and I were just trying to do what needed to be done. At least that is what it felt like at the time. The managers who reported to me would tell me they needed more of my support. I wanted to be tough for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day, while I was traveling, there was a long email chain where one of my managers was under attack. Evan, Snap&amp;rsquo;s CEO, was on the chain and untrue things were being said about my team&amp;rsquo;s work. It felt like we were spending more time defending than building and it was hurting morale on the team. I assumed the worst of intentions when I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have. I lashed out and I crashed out. I said &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve had enough of the peanut gallery&amp;rdquo; and told people they need to stay in their lane. I was pissed. And I wasn&amp;rsquo;t thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had thought about sending emails like that in the past, but never had. I had always deleted them, but for some reason I didn&amp;rsquo;t this time. As soon as I sent the email, I received several Snaps from colleagues who were concerned. &amp;ldquo;What are you doing? Are you ok?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Did you not know Evan was on the thread?&amp;rdquo; And, Evan called me out, and said my email didn&amp;rsquo;t reflect the values of his company. And I was hurt, and I was mad. But I agreed and I apologized. I was trying to be heroic but I made things worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-myth-of-monotonic-progression&#34;&gt;The myth of monotonic progression&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve interviewed a lot of technical executives over the years. They will tell stories like the above. Well polished. Authentic. Raw enough to feel vulnerable, but nothing too damning. Always with an implied growth that they won&amp;rsquo;t repeat that mistake. The worst stories far enough in the past to show that&amp;rsquo;s not who they are anymore. Like each war story and battle scar has slowly chiseled out pieces of their humanity and all that is now left is the perfect corporate robot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaders tend to see the politics that happen in their organizations through an abstract lens because they are distanced from it. I don&amp;rsquo;t believe the execs are so quick to dismiss this type of behavior just because they&amp;rsquo;ve seen it all. I think the nature of their role allows them distance. They aren&amp;rsquo;t facing the comments directly. They aren&amp;rsquo;t in the fight. And when they are, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen them react in the same way. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen senior executives throw away millions of dollars of company money because the alternative was telling a peer they screwed up. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen senior executives fake data to make a red goal turn green because they didn&amp;rsquo;t feel the psychological safety to show weakness. As much as they pretend otherwise, senior leaders are just as human and fallible as the rest of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not excusing any of the bad behavior here. I&amp;rsquo;m just not pretending it doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist. We worry so much about being perfect, but that isn&amp;rsquo;t the goal. We just need to be better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;reflecting-on-epistemic-crises&#34;&gt;Reflecting on epistemic crises&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, I teach. Being a teacher doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you are perfect. If it was, nobody would be qualified to be one. The goal is to help people grow. You don&amp;rsquo;t grow by avoiding failure. You grow by encountering failure, reflecting on it, working through why, and learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of my students start every quarter groaning about the fact that I always assign group projects. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s hard dealing with other people&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Can&amp;rsquo;t I just do it on my own? It&amp;rsquo;d be easier&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;I have no friends in the class&amp;rdquo;. I know the complaints well, because I also hated group projects as a student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I give them though because they are difficult and I want students to run into these human-relationship problems so we can then work through it together. So we can reflect. And I hope they become better people as a result. A little less susceptible to tribalism. A little more aware of how to deal with abuse if it does happen. Everything I&amp;rsquo;ve struggled with in professional environments over my career. We are all heroes of our own stories, but when we work with others, those stories come into conflict. With often disastrous results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growing up is learning to question ourselves but to also trust ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-i-wrote-this&#34;&gt;Why I wrote this&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was difficult for me to write. I&amp;rsquo;m used to offering up problems and then solutions; in this case trying to make some tidy solution cheapens the reality of these situations. I worry people will think I’m looking for sympathy. I honestly don&amp;rsquo;t think about these things much anymore and they aren&amp;rsquo;t raw anymore. When I was in each of these moments it was hard though. And worse, I felt alone. My hope in writing this is someone in a similar situation will feel a little less alone. That you realize abuse is not ok. It is also something we are all prone to committing or being complicit in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These moments stick out to me because they were rare. This is the worst of 20+ years of working in tech. I worked with wonderful people, funny people, kind people. People are generally good. But here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned about the epistemology of being an asshole: you never know when you are one. Not really. In each of these stories, I thought I was justified. The others were clueless. Jake was just passionate. I was protecting my team. It&amp;rsquo;s only from a distance that I can see clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s why, as much as I love tech, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be put in that context again. It is easy to talk about this stuff from a distance. I&amp;rsquo;m detached enough from corporate life that I can be clinical about it. If I started at a new company tomorrow and was leading a big organization, my blood pressure would still rise, I&amp;rsquo;d still have people that annoyed me, I&amp;rsquo;d still be subject to tribalist thoughts. Maturity is not the absence of biases. It&amp;rsquo;s figuring out how to still move forward without hurting people and hurting yourself. And you&amp;rsquo;ll still falter sometimes but you reflect, and figure out how to do a little better next time. And for me, I think it means realizing as much as I love tech, I don’t want to be in the thick of it anymore because I&amp;rsquo;m afraid of the person I am when I&amp;rsquo;m in it. I just hope I can help others navigate the journey better than I could.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
